<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title></title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>&quot;Back to base-ics&quot;</title>
        <published>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/back-to-base-ics/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/back-to-base-ics/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/back-to-base-ics/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;from the desk of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;planet-nine-app&#x2F;planet-nine&quot;&gt;planetnineisaspaceship&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-s-in-a-name&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-s-in-a-name&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-s-in-a-name&quot;&gt;What&#x27;s in a name?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ursula K. Le Guin&#x27;s fantastic A Wizard of Earthsea creates a world of magic where the greatest power one can hold over a person or thing is knowledge of its true name.
A friend of mine and I were lamenting that we never had the opportunity to run in to Le Guin while we were all in Portland (he&#x27;s a big deal enough that this was a possibility, I am not).
He also shared with me her essay on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;monoskop.org&#x2F;images&#x2F;9&#x2F;96&#x2F;Le_Guin_Ursula_K_1986_1989_The_Carrier_Bag_Theory_of_Fiction.pdf&quot;&gt;The Carrier Bag Theory of Fiction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of you familiar with Planet Nine&#x27;s lore will know that boats feature quite heavily.
Boats have two properties that make them useful: they float, and they carry things from here to there.
If we relax our definition of floating to include being carried, I hope you&#x27;ll indulge me in acknowledging that the carrier bag, and the boat have much in common.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I&#x27;d like to note too that Le Guinn acknowledges the importance of stacks in her essay, &quot;home being another, larger
kind of pouch or bag, a container for people.&quot;
Anyone who has been drinking with me as I try to explain stacks and boats will recognize this flexibility in terminology)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the theory, which comes from Elizabeth Fisher&#x27;s Carrier Bag Theory of Human Evolution, is that though bags [and boats] are essential to humans, so much so that they were likely our earliest tool, they don&#x27;t fit in well with the conflict-driven hero narratives of modern fiction.
Hero worship is not just in fiction, but I would say permeates all of popular culture in the United States--whether quarterback, or diva, or pedophile-turned-president--whereas carrier bags are things you get when you donate twenty bucks to PBS, which normally you wouldn&#x27;t do, but now you have to because of that stupid president.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Guin writes in her essay:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One relationship among elements in the novel may well be that of
conflict, but the reduction of narrative to conflict is absurd. (I have
read a how-to-write manual that said, &quot;A story should be seen as a
battle,&quot; and went on about strategies, attacks, victory, etc.) Conflict,
competition, stress, struggle, etc., within the narrative conceived as
carrier bag I belly I box I house I medicine bundle, may be seen as
necessary elements of a whole which itself cannot be characterized
either as conflict or as harmony, since its purpose is neither resolution nor stasis but continuing process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it&#x27;s clear that the Hero does not look well in this bag. He
needs a stage or a pedestal or a pinnacle. You put him in a bag and
he looks like a rabbit, like a potato.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This notion of narrative as a &lt;em&gt;continuing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; process is intriguing.
Aren&#x27;t stories, by definition, in possession of an ending?
But robbed of the need for resolution, why not just go on and on?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People haven&#x27;t been writing computer programs nearly as long as we&#x27;ve been writing stories so we don&#x27;t really know what we&#x27;re doing yet, and it&#x27;s probably unfair to map the latter to the former.
But I don&#x27;t think it&#x27;s too far afield to say that the world of Facebook and Google has it&#x27;s own hero-fetish that might not be the greatest when the story doesn&#x27;t end.
&quot;You either die a hero or live long enough to see yourself become the villain,&quot; Harvey Dent was on to something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the gigantocorps are our heroes, constantly on stage peacocking about like the world owes them for their benevolence, what&#x27;s the carrier bag for tech?
On Earthsea we would only have to speak its name to avail ourselves of its power.
Here on plain old Earth we need that name, and then we have to build it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an idea of what it might be.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We call it a &lt;strong&gt;base&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;billions-and-billions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#billions-and-billions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: billions-and-billions&quot;&gt;Billions and billions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the interwebs was kicking off the dotcom boom, there were six billion or so people on the planet.
Twenty-six years later there are eight billion.
In real life, we call this increase a triumph of modern medicine, in the biz we call it a scaling problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to bore yourself nauseous for an hour, go look up system design interview prep where some dude from a faang (this acronym is for Facebook (now Meta), Apple, Amazon, Netflix, and Google (now Alphabet). Originally Netflix, whose market cap is a fraction of the others, was included so as to avoid the unfortunate F-word acronym without it, but given Facebook being Meta now, perhaps there is a four-letter acronym that could be used instead. I leave the anagraming of that as an exercise for the reader) company takes you through building out some system with eleventy-billion users and how cool they all are to have eleventy-billion users.
He&#x27;ll let you know that you need to handle a gazillion api calls an hour, and a gajillion bytes of data per call so that they can check that you know what Amazon Web Service you need to handle that kind of volume since you&#x27;re definitely not building it yourself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Claude, here are the top ten apps by Monthly Active Users (MAUs):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook - 3.07 billion MAU Most Popular Social Media Apps in 2025 | Piktochart&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube - 2.54 billion MAU Most Popular Social Media Platforms &amp;amp; Apps (2025)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WhatsApp - 2 billion MAU (some sources report up to 3 billion)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instagram - 2 billion MAU Most Popular Social Media Apps in 2025 | Piktochart&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WeChat - 1.38 billion MAU (primarily China)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok - 1.59 billion MAU Most Popular Social Media Apps in 2025 | Piktochart&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook Messenger - 947 million MAU&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telegram - ~800 million MAU (estimated)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snapchat - ~750 million MAU (estimated)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X (formerly Twitter) - 556 million MAU&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I trust these numbers as much as a Bernie named Madhoff, but let&#x27;s just take them and do some math.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there&#x27;s a steep drop off from one to ten, and if we assume that whatever we&#x27;re building is not going to hit billion user scale immediately, maybe we can take half a billion as a starting point.
Now 500 million feels like a big number, but if we divide it by the thirty days in a month we get 16 million DAUs.
DAUs are of course higher than that, so, in order to make the math easier, let&#x27;s say its 24 million.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s a million users per hour if we assume a smooth average, and that&#x27;s 277 users per second.
If all of those users are making like four to five api calls that&#x27;s about a thousand per second.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;rpi5.png&quot; alt=&quot;A raspberry pi 5 held in front of a gorgeous landscape. It fits in the palm of a hand&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
The latest in the Raspberry Pi line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guy above is a Raspberry Pi 5.
It costs a hundred dollars, and can handle a thousand api call per second no sweat.
I don&#x27;t know, let&#x27;s say I&#x27;m off by a factor of ten and twitter does ten thousand api calls per second.
Do you think nazi musk can afford ten of these bad boys?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question then is what do these companies need with the gigantic datacenters they&#x27;re actually using.
As anyone whose had an empty drawer in their house knows, nature abhors a vaccuum.
If you&#x27;re paying for computers and storage, you better be using and filling them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#x27;s what they&#x27;re doing, filling them with every single last piece of data on &lt;em&gt;you&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that they can.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&#x27;re not doing four or five api calls per user, they&#x27;re making forty or fifty, tracking every last millisecond you spend on posts and videos.
Did you go down, and then up?
Did you tap for more info, check the poster&#x27;s profile, like, love, downvote, favorite, swipe, breathe heavily, tremble at all, you name it they&#x27;re grabbing it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why not?
They don&#x27;t even need to pay people to analyze the data anymore.
They just feed it to more machines to determine what combination of colors and words and graphics will get you purchasing more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have to do this to pay themselves and their investors, and now that they&#x27;re buying islands and rocket ships, the checks they expect look like those numbers above: billions and billions.
Sagan wrote a book with that title, which starts by explaining he would never use that term because it&#x27;s too imprecise.
And he was a cosmologist thinking about the universe.
If there aren&#x27;t even billions and billions of things in &lt;em&gt;space&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, what the heck are they doing in a handful of people&#x27;s bank accounts?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things get like that, you&#x27;re supposed to be able to create competition to the giant firms, but how can you possibly compete with a platform serving half of the population of the Earth?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well first we have to answer what&#x27;s competition?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pin-factory&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-pin-factory&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-pin-factory&quot;&gt;The pin factory&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In The Wealth of Nations by Adam Smith, his first example is a pin factory.
It was a good in high demand back in the eighteenth century.
One with clear inputs, and outputs, and not a whole lot of reason for global distribution.
There weren&#x27;t technological improvements other than in the manufacturing process, and the labor wasn&#x27;t particularly skilled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about the economics of the eighteenth century: you couldn&#x27;t move pins around the globe at close to the speed of light.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules of microeconomics where firms are bounded by location, and materials, are no more in a world where bits and bytes flow through tubes unfettered.
How on Earth, pun intended, do you start a business to compete with a business that can deliver its &quot;goods&quot; instantaneously to everyone?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the biz we talk about &quot;products.&quot;
The product is the thing that you sell, as in the thing your customers give you money for.
Do you give Meta money to use Instagram?
Who does?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously its advertisers, and behind advertisers are businesses.
They buy ads, but what is it they&#x27;re buying?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it reach?
Is it the demographics?
Well let&#x27;s talk about both of those.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach is the whole kit and caboodle for the internet.
The promise that everyone in the whole world can buy what you&#x27;re selling just by you buying a domain name and setting up a small site is just as awesome today as it was thirty years ago.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the gigantocorp platforms grew and grew, it became harder and harder (or more expensive) to break through the noise.
After a while, the only way for your marketing dollars to hit the ROI (return on investment) they were looking for was to &quot;go viral.&quot;
Guess what happens when you go viral.
Your website tips over, and you run out of inventory, and a bunch of people get pissed, and it&#x27;s like the lottery winner who&#x27;s broke two years later because they can&#x27;t figure out how to stay rich.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about demographics?
Facebook boasts four billion MAUs, and Instagram half of that.
If you&#x27;re marketing something though I think you already know which app you&#x27;re marketing on.
Before the internet, people would self-select into spaces and media to consume, and there wasn&#x27;t much of a need for further segmenting within groups.
There&#x27;s not a huge overlap between the people walking into Hot Topic, and the ones walking into Abercrombie and Fitch, and there&#x27;s no real need for those brands to intrude on blog posts becase the people who like them, will find them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of digital advertising is that we know everything about everyone, and thus can put exactly what they want to see right in front of them.
It is a ridiculous premise, which is why it&#x27;s so lucrative.
Because it&#x27;s the modern equivalent of a rainmaker.
Did your campaign fail to make it rain because the advertisers suck, or because you didn&#x27;t spend enough?
If there&#x27;s no competition, there&#x27;s only one variable in your campaign to change you know?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#x27;s our premise.
The selling points of digital advertising are reach, their ability to attract large numbers of humans to their platforms, and demographics, their knowledge of who you are and what you&#x27;re looking to buy right now.
And that, currently, they suck, but no one&#x27;s figured out how to do these two points better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reach&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#reach&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: reach&quot;&gt;Reach&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;starbucks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parker Posey from Best In Show explaining how she met her husband at the Starbucks across the street&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&quot;We met at Starbucks. Not the same Starbucks, it was actually the Starbucks across the street...&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s fun to make fun of the Starbucks across the street from each other, but there&#x27;s actually a pretty good reason for it.
Most stores come equipped with two point-of-sale (POS) systems, and there&#x27;s a maximum to how many customers can go through those systems.
So if a store hits that max, you open another store across the street.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how scaling works with computers too, and a lot of time, money, and energy is put into making sure that the machines that a platform runs on all work the same, and give people the same experience.
You don&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;see&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the instagram across the street, but that&#x27;s what&#x27;s happening.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s no reason why you couldn&#x27;t see it though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who have never played a Massively Multiplayer Online game, here&#x27;s what you see when you first sign up:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;realmchoice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The realm selection screen from World of Warcraft&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
As you can see, there are quite a few Starbucks on this street (this is the World of Warcraft server selection screen).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the engineering side of things, instagram and WoW are more or less the same.
Tons of users, tons of computation needed to serve the users, and a need for this system to never fail.
The difference is that WoW users expect a little more control their experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what&#x27;s interesting in the MMO is that users are persistent characters, so even though the realm they choose has the same software, the &lt;em&gt;state&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of the realm is unique to the realm.
You can see a number of PvP realms where players can fight each other.
Each one of those has some sort of mini-culture around its PvP, which can define and change the game pretty significantly.
Sort of like how the baristas at the Starbucks across the street might affect which one you go to (no, she&#x27;s not interested in you, she&#x27;s just being nice).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instagram doesn&#x27;t want its users to create anything like that because it undermines their ability to control what is displayed to its users.
Control over what is displayed to its users is how Instagram sells advertising, which is how they make money.
So, what is Instagram&#x27;s product?
It looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;orange.avif&quot; alt=&quot;The ending scene from Clockwork Orange when Alex is forced to watch propoganda&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
At least the good people in Kubrick&#x27;s world were kind enough to make the science tapping into your brain visible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe there&#x27;s room to play with this realm idea though.
Give the users a little more control over what content they consume, and maybe even make it so people can setup their own realms like some games like Minecraft do.
Not sure how to monetize it though, but we can punt on that for now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;demographics&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#demographics&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: demographics&quot;&gt;Demographics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live in Portland, Oregon, and in the early tens and teens of this second millenium, there was a great show called Portlandia.
In the first or second episode, a proprietor of a feminist book store tells Steve Buscemi that he should head to a puzzle store to find what he&#x27;s looking for.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shocked Buscemi asks, &quot;where is there a puzzle store?&quot;
The proprietor responds by listing off all the locations where there are puzzle stores.
It cracks me up every time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there puzzle stores where you live?
I&#x27;m guessing probably not.
They&#x27;re kind of peculiar to the kind of place where grown ups take pride in being big wholesome kids and grandparents at the same time and&#x2F;or smoke enough weed to require a steady stream of jigsawed cardboard to stay busy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you&#x27;re a puzzler in need of a fix, and you&#x27;ve just moved to Portland you might google up the nearest puzzle store, and then head to it.
We&#x27;ll get to &lt;strong&gt;search&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in a second.
Chances are though, you found out about puzzle stores the same way as Buscemi on Portlandia: word of mouth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketers will tell you that nothing beats word of mouth, but I don&#x27;t think we need to ask them why.
Who&#x27;re you going to trust to best understand your puzzling needs?
A system of cold, and uncaring machines programmed by cold and uncaring people, or your friends?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friends know you better than the machine, and more importantly know the context through which you&#x27;re asking.
The answer to, &quot;I need a puzzle stat!&quot; and &quot;I need a puzzle for my nephew&#x27;s birthday.&quot; might be different.
The machine doesn&#x27;t understand your context when you search for, &quot;puzzle stores near me,&quot; but your friends do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well that&#x27;s not entirely true.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s actually quite a bit that the machines are doing to try and understand that context.
Is your nephew&#x27;s birthday in google calendar?
Well then the machines know you might be looking for puzzles for his gift.
Did you get a receipt sent to your gmail after your last puzzle purchase?
Well then the machines know about your puzzle addiction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does writing a truly massive amount of software in order to spy on all digital communiques to attempt to extract what our friends do for us for free seem like an incredible waste of time and resources?
Perhaps not, perhaps it&#x27;s so successful that we humans have embraced our Orwellian present so as to more efficiently purchase socks.
Let us check the average click-through rate of the ads served by Google and Meta, companies whose combined market cap would put them seventh, between the UK and France, in national GDP.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a lot of blah blah blah, and it&#x27;s impossible to get a real number because these two companies are basically giant deception machines, but it&#x27;s somewhere between 1 and 2 percent.
Let&#x27;s call it 1.5%.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often do you click on the stuff your friends send you?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we&#x27;re going to start talking about my stack here, and while I&#x27;ve gotten tons of help, it&#x27;s still sort of mine to shepherd for now, and so I&#x27;d like to make something quite clear.
I think you, like all people, are cool and interesting, but if I&#x27;m going to get to know you it&#x27;s going to be over coffee or beers some time, and not through the systematic harvesting and exploitative usage of your personal data.
I have neither the interest nor the time to do so, and I don&#x27;t really trust myself to protect your personal data &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.breachsense.com&#x2F;breaches&#x2F;&quot;&gt;from the 1337 h4x0rz of the world&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of collecting all of this stuff and using it to ruin the internet, the idea is to let your friends do that work like they already do, and just give them a piece of the action.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-cities&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#a-tale-of-two-cities&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: a-tale-of-two-cities&quot;&gt;A tale of two cities&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Portland is known for a good many things, but let&#x27;s focus on two right now: our general love of the outdoors--specifically those of us who like to climb things--and our sizable lesbian population.
There are a number of products in the world that cater to these two groups, subaru outbacks being one of the most noticeable, but for our discussion here I&#x27;d like to talk about just one.
The humble carabiner.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;carabiners.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A variety of carabiners on display&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
Whether it&#x27;s helping you survive a fall to gravity, or a fall to love, this little guy&#x27;s gonna have an outsized impact for the cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a variety of reasons, the carabiner is of rather significant importance to the two groups above.
If you&#x27;re not part of those groups already though, do you have any idea what the difference is between all of those carabiners?
I don&#x27;t, and it&#x27;s not entirely clear where I might go to learn.
For some things it&#x27;s fine to rely on trial and error, but are you ready to trust your life, romantically or otherwise, to fate?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&#x27;s say I&#x27;m a fashion-conscious rock-climbing lesbian with a degree in mechanical engineering, and a passion for metalurgy.
I start a blog called Tie the Metal Knot about finding love and carabiners in the Portland bouldering scene.
I should of course be compensated for my expertise, and to do so I load up my poor blog with ad cancer, of which I see a fraction of a penny for every person who lands on the page.
I also go through the hassle of becoming an affiliate at Amazon so I can get a dime from carabiners sold through my site should someone wade through the swamp of ads and actually find them, at least until that link dies because Amazon killed my preferred carabiner store&#x27;s business, and now it&#x27;s just a dead link amongst all the other garbage that covers up my thoughtful and interesting prose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably don&#x27;t even need to show you a screenshot of a site set up like this, but I&#x27;m going to anyways:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;blog.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a site taken over by two popups&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
Was gonna show you the ads, but can&#x27;t even do that with this barely dismissable popup asking for your personal information.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis is that all of our sites are like this because there isn&#x27;t a better alternative.
If we can find a way to monetize sites as much or more through another mechanism then people will adopt that.
But, if you make it an either&#x2F;or then you need to grow big enough to compete with everyone with a gmail and&#x2F;or facebook account.
That&#x27;s pretty much everyone on Earth with a computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of making it either&#x2F;or we worked out a way to make it whichever works better.
If you want ad-infested garbage in front of you all the time, you can keep on doing what you&#x27;ve always done.
If you want a cleaner interface that can make more &lt;em&gt;people&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and not gigantocorps money, then read on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-about-that-base&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#all-about-that-base&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: all-about-that-base&quot;&gt;All about that base&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;&#x2F;head&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Hello World
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;&#x2F;body&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;&#x2F;html&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ^^^ is a website.
Your device and its browser are called the client.
The computer that these words come from is called a server.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you type realultimatepower.net into your browser&#x27;s url bar, a number of computers talk to each other to figure out where that server is and get you the words that are that website (feel free to check it out, it&#x27;s pretty sweet).
The problem is that computers, as powerful as they are, are still finite so if your website is super popular and&#x2F;or does a lot of things, you need a bunch of servers.
That can get expensive, and people aren&#x27;t big on paying for things on the internet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there&#x27;s no real reason why the words that are a website can&#x27;t come from different servers.
In fact that&#x27;s how it works right now.
There are plenty of servers serving up google for example.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what you don&#x27;t see all that much is servers serving the same words from different domain names.
That&#x27;s the thing those game servers are doing.
And it&#x27;s the thing the Fediverse does with Mastodon, Pixelfed, and Lemmy.[^1]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s great, but they&#x27;re all still doing something that&#x27;s not the best for users, namely keeping everything you do around forever and ever.
There&#x27;s value to the platform in the permanence of the things people have and create on them, because that&#x27;s what these platforms are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether servers in the Fediverse, or Bluesky are selling this data or not is debatable.
That they&#x27;re being scraped, for free, by tons and tons of other platforms for data is not.
As the platforms grow, they become more expensive to run, and even Mark Cuban&#x27;s Bluesky money is finite, especially if he runs for president, so how do you foresee them monetizing should they live long enough to become the villain?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I on the other hand, and again I want this to be crystal clear, do not care what you had for brunch back in 2012.
I don&#x27;t think that should have much bearing on either of our lives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, someone&#x27;s gotta pay to run the servers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either I build a platform that steals your data and sells it to advertisers to sell it to businesses for businesses to sell you stuff, or you buy stuff and that pays for the servers somehow.
Y&#x27;all probably buy stuff online already, we just need a way to make sure the server gets paid when you do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in the real world when the puzzle store gets too busy, someone opens a puzzle store across the street.
People sort of self-select which puzzle store they pick, mostly because crossing the street is onerous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the digital world, people usually don&#x27;t have visibility to which side of the street their server&#x27;s on.
And when they do, like with the game servers, they usually have to pick one and stick with it so you don&#x27;t lose all your stuff.
But if you don&#x27;t have stuff to lose, what&#x27;s to stop you from just picking whatever server&#x27;s closest, or fastest, or pays you the most, or is run by your buddy?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of server is what I&#x27;m calling a base.
And it belongs to us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;base-and-essence&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#base-and-essence&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: base-and-essence&quot;&gt;Base and essence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In philosophy there&#x27;s a distinction between what a thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (essence), and what it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (function).
In software, pretty much everyone cares about essence because at a pretty fundamental level the function of computers is all the same: bytes moving around and doing things.
A base has no inherent essence, it only has function.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that function is to monetize content creation through user transactions to businesses directly without the need for advertisement-based discovery.
Allow me to show you the pictures of what I mean.
Here is the current monetization flow of the internet:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;ad-flow.svg&quot; alt=&quot;A picture of the transaction flow on the internet currently. Businesses pay advertisers who pay content platforms who revenue share with content creators, a needlessly convoluted system that screws humans and lines the pockets of already wealthy people&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this picture users and content creators are linked to businesses via advertisers and content platforms.
Again, most of us buy stuff online, it&#x27;s not that we want &lt;em&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; businesses to go away, but having the advertisers and content platforms as the link between us makes businesses, and consumers beholden to them for our needs.
Beholden is just another word for exploitable.
And in economics, whenever you can exploit a resource, you&#x27;re going to be making money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, we&#x27;re talking about what a base &lt;em&gt;does&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, not what it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
Here&#x27;s the picture:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-to-base-ics&#x2F;.&#x2F;base.svg&quot; alt=&quot;A picture of the transaction flow with bases. There&amp;#39;s money flowing to people and not spyware gigantocorps&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
Please note the use of the color green to indicate money flowing into your pockets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what a base &lt;em&gt;does&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it lets you join along with other members of whatever group&#x2F;community&#x2F;horde might care about the base to figure out ways of buying things on the internet that pays the group&#x2F;community&#x2F;horde and not already rich dudes buying up land in Hawaii.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How it does this is up to the group&#x2F;community&#x2F;horde that uses it.
You wanna create a gaming store community where everyone gets a piece of the action when some hot new cardboard drops?
Go for it.
You wanna create a safe space for new parents to exchange hand-me-downs, and share in the profit when someone just has to have a brand new stroller?
You can do that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bases are easy to join, and easy to leave.
Don&#x27;t want to hear about the latest SCOTUS news for one freaking minute?
Just leave that base.
Need to get your fix after you cool down?
Rejoin the base.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different platforms can drift off the same bases, and you can have multiple versions of the same platform connected to different bases.
Don&#x27;t want to think about all of this?
Just join a base where someone else thinks about it for you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t have all the answers, so I&#x27;m not going to build a system that tries to tell you what to do.
I just want to build a system that takes money from gigantocorps and gives it to you.
This is what I came up with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know how everything&#x27;s getting more expensive?
How those great spaces for kids, and cafes that won&#x27;t kick you out for just having a coffee keep closing?
How you really want to buy from anywhere but Amazon, but man is it just too convenient to be able to order from your couch, and have some overworked and underpaid blue-vest-wearing sap run up your walk so they can stay on their delivery schedule?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A base is just a computer, and computers can be small.
Look up.
Could you stick a shelf up above eye level with a machine or two on it processing transactions, and making you, or your favorite cafe, or a non-profit you contribute to money?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;packetstream.io&quot;&gt;People are already doing this with home servers, but they&#x27;re renting them out to folks so they can scrape data around the internet for advertising.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be the change you want to see.
Start a base with your friends, make money, tell google, amazon, and meta to kick rocks.
If it doesn&#x27;t work, you turn the computer off and hand it to your niece or nephew to play roblox on or something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make a dollar though, and I don&#x27;t know anything about you, it will make me so happy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So don&#x27;t tell me about it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell your friends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the Hero has decreed through his mouthpieces the
Lawgivers, first, that the proper shape of the narrative is that of the
arrow or spear, starting here and going straight there and THOK!
hitting its mark (which drops dead); second, that the central concern of narrative, including the novel, is conflict; and third, that the
story isn&#x27;t any good if he isn&#x27;t in it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t want to be a hero, and there is no narrative arc here.
I just think it&#x27;s high time the regular folk had a carrier bag (or boat!) of there own.
One they can load up with bananas, and socks, and mall ninja shit, and empty at home without having to sign their life away to companies the size of governments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s why I go by planetnineisaspaceship.
I&#x27;m easy enough to find if you&#x27;d like, it&#x27;s not a very effective pseudonym.
It&#x27;s a reminder that the spaceship, the boat, the carrier bag is the purpose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve setup a server before, or even if you haven&#x27;t you can check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;planet-nine-app&#x2F;allyabase&quot;&gt;allyabase repo here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&#x27;t setup a server before, I&#x27;d recommend watching a video or two on how to setup a minecraft server as those usually have what you need in them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system is in production, but also a definite work in progress.
If you run into any issues find me on discord or email me at zach at planetnine dot app.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]: If you&#x27;ve never heard of the Fediverse, it can be overwhelming to dive into it. So I recommend not doing that unless you&#x27;re in for some deep cut tech.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>&quot;It&#x27;s a free country&quot;</title>
        <published>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/its-a-free-country/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/its-a-free-country/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/its-a-free-country/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;from the desk of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.planetnineisaspaceship.com&quot;&gt;planetnineisaspaceship&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;it-s-a-free-country&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#it-s-a-free-country&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: it-s-a-free-country&quot;&gt;&quot;It&#x27;s a free country&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2015 I bought a house in southeast Portland with a friend.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had the benefit of both having gone to a small college in town called Reed.
Reed is well known for its academics, and somewhat lax approach to substance use (at least it was back in our day).
Those of us who went there are governed by the Honor Principle, an ill-defined set of rules that mostly amount to &quot;don&#x27;t be an asshole.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True to our youthful indoctrination, we drew up an agreement with provisions on what should happen if either of us got a real girlfriend, but which was a bit light on what will happen financially upon sale of our joint asset.
So when it came time to sell The Dojo, an affectionate nickname earned by the Asian decor that pre-dated our purchase, I consulted my lawyer, another Reedie, on what the legal and financial ramifications of the sale would be.
Our conversation went something like this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: So what I blah blah blah like if I could just write a check blah blah.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyer: Oh yeah, you can do that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me (flabbergasted): What do you mean?
I can just write a check like that to him?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My lawyer smiled that smile that only lawyers smile when they&#x27;ve just lawyered the shit out of something, and spread his arms wide.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyer: Of course!
It&#x27;s a free country.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That friend and I still cheers to the day I wrote him a six figure check, deposited it, and then went across the street to The Lutz, our alma mater&#x27;s goto watering hole to celebrate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;its-a-free-country&#x2F;lutz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The exterior of one of the finest establishments in Portland&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-t-you-just-like-not-do-that&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#can-t-you-just-like-not-do-that&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: can-t-you-just-like-not-do-that&quot;&gt;&quot;Can&#x27;t you just like, not do that?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my twenties I worked for two well-regarded gigantocorps, one involving coffee and the other named after a fruit.
Both of them, while touting how great they were for employees, were aggressively anti-union.
Sitting in a room making $24&#x2F;hr and listening to some lawyer making $300&#x2F;hr tell you how the folks making $13&#x2F;hr should shut up and like it so that the folks making $0&#x2F;hr because they&#x27;re already millionaires can make more money wouldn&#x27;t be the worst place to start the revolution.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, of course, was already well on my way to starting The Revolution, and so my take away from that meeting was, why on Earth does every stupid company do this?
Like, can&#x27;t you just not do that?
Well it kind of turns out that you can&#x27;t.
Sort of.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&#x27;t until much later in my career that I learned that corporate titles have actual meaning beyond conferring muckity muck status to mostly incompetent white men.
For example, Directors and above in publicly traded companies have a fiduciary responsibility to the company, and thus the shareholders of that company.
Fiduciary means acting in the financial best interest of the company.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any fledgling day trader will tell you that making moves that are in the financial best interest of anything is more art (luck) than skill, but there is something pretty universally understood as bad for a company&#x27;s bottom line: paying its workers more.
This means that by law, Directors and above at publicly traded companies must be anti-union.
Of course union busting is illegal too so the real advantage lies with the group that can employ the most lawyers to figure out what can and cannot be done.
And if you&#x27;re wondering if it would just be cheaper to pay people more than employ all the lawyers needed to fight this ongoing battle just remember that if there&#x27;s any group better at getting paid than unions, it&#x27;s lawyers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time that this was going on at the fruit stand, as we called that fruit-named company, its stock price was rocketing up in value.
I invested the ten percent max into the employee stock purchase plan, and after two years of that I had enough to go back to school.
That whole experience got me thinking about shareholders and employees, and really what is the value to society of people with enough wealth to invest in the stock market being the only ones to benefit from it?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well what if the shareholders of a company weren&#x27;t rich people, but rather, like, not rich people?
I thought I had come up with something novel, but it turns out the idea&#x27;s been around for a while.
They&#x27;re called cooperatives, and the oldest one still around in the US was started by a guy named Ben Franklin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-t-we-all-just-get-along&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#can-t-we-all-just-get-along&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: can-t-we-all-just-get-along&quot;&gt;Can&#x27;t we all just get along?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are, if you&#x27;re in the US, your introduction to cooperatives has been through tiny grocery stores with a bit of something for every restrictive diet in existence.
These are great, but there&#x27;s actually a much more common cooperative, and those are credit unions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only are credit unions more common in the US than other coops, but they&#x27;re actually pretty common around the world.
That makes sense since it&#x27;s actually pretty hard to make money as a bank unless you&#x27;re serving people who have a bunch of money, and a bunch of money is not something all that many people on Earth have.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about US corporate law is that corporations are very easy to own a piece of.
Unlike moving money around, shares in a company can be owned and traded without a whole lot of problems.
This cavalier attitude towards the shared ownership of a corporate structures extends to cooperatives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-you-know-you-can-just-not-do-that&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#did-you-know-you-can-just-not-do-that&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: did-you-know-you-can-just-not-do-that&quot;&gt;Did you know you can just not do that?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve never worked for an early stage company, I&#x27;d imagine you probably aren&#x27;t too familiar with how a cap table works.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;its-a-free-country&#x2F;cap-table.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A dumb spreadsheet with made up numbers to keep rich people rich&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of a company, before it starts making money, people work for under market value and a piece of the pie.
The conceit is that, should the company be successful, the piece plus salary should exceed what you would&#x27;ve made had you worked a regular job.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competing for these pieces then are all these employees, the investors, and the founders of the company, each of whom have an incentive for their pieces to stay as big as possible.
No startup I&#x27;ve ever worked for has shown me the cap table, but I&#x27;ll vouch for the fact that when it works, it&#x27;s not the worst way to make a buck.
That is until you realize that you made a whole bunch of other people ten bucks.
Then you have to wrestle with whether they deserved it, or were just being greedy dickheads.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bring this up to talk about the bajillionairs of our era.
Bezos, for example, owned nearly 50% of Amazon when it IPOed back in 1997.
This ownership is where the majority of his wealth comes from.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promise of capitalism is that.
Not that you&#x27;ll get paid a lot, but rather that you make something so valuable that you become a gajillionaire because of it.
I&#x27;m sure we all have our opinions on the morality of this, but you can hardly argue with the efficacy.
There&#x27;s a seemingly endless supply of greedy dickheads trying to become billionaires too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But did you know, and this was kind of surprising to me when I first started looking into it, that you don&#x27;t have to be a greedy dickhead?
There is no fiduciary responsibility to yourself.
You do not need to hold on to your equity like Smaug buried deep in the Lonely Mountain hoarding his horde.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would happen if someone made Amazon, but gave that near 50% out to the employees and then users of Amazon?
I don&#x27;t really know, but it kind of feels like it&#x27;s worth finding out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-we-need-them-or-do-they-need-us&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#do-we-need-them-or-do-they-need-us&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: do-we-need-them-or-do-they-need-us&quot;&gt;Do we need them, or do they need us?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the wonderful good fortune of getting into punk rock as a teenager in the Chicagoland area in the late 90s.
Thus my class consciousness was awakened through reading the liner notes of bands like Dillinger Four, and The Broadways.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst all of the veritable jams from that time, [We&#x27;ll Have a Party][party] by The Broadways (Brendan Kelly and Chris McCaughan of The Lawrence Arms&#x27; Yardbirds) became my life&#x27;s ballad over time.
The song&#x27;s a love story put on hold as the system is torn down.
Every line is gold, provoking thought and consideration of just how ludicrous and desperate the system can be.
Go listen.
I&#x27;ll wait.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the stanza for this post:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bosses learned to fool the slaves into 8 hour days
But do we need them or do they need us?
Seems like we dwell on these useless things, lifestyles of wealth, pursuit of money
Competition says to beat each other down for personal gain&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the fruit stand sell iPods if we all quit?
Of course.
Does my first startup sell transit tickets without even one member of the people who took a pay cut to keep the company going?
Maybe...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the equity payout for the founders justified at 10 times that of early employees?
What about 100 times that?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keynes in the riveting (&#x2F;s) General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money, points out that the Classical Economic notion that Labor negotiates for real wages based on its productivity is undermined by the fact that Labor has to negotiate for actual real world wages that, you know, let you buy food and stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more well-known Marx had already pointed out that Labor was getting stiffed out of the fruits of its labor since profit was going to the bosses instead of to themselves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in a capitalist society, the pressure from the bosses is to get you coming and going.
Labor is underpaid, and then the profit garnered from that injustice is spread amongst the already wealthy.
And for a few centuries now, the goal we&#x27;ve been sold on is joining their club, and not marching them to the guillotines.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to my first startup, and someone leaving.
Does Bezos&#x27; life change all that much if his 50% becomes 48% because he had to spend a bit more to retain someone, or replace someone?
How much does your life change if tomorrow you stopped getting paid?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s the inequality in entrepreneurialship.
Bezos has to roll the dice on having a few less billions than all his billions.
You have to roll the dice on whether you get to afford food next week.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems like we need them more than they need us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And before anyone tries to say, oh but Bezos was risking it all, let&#x27;s remember how his parents gave him six figures early in the company&#x27;s history.
Six figures is probably what I&#x27;ve given my therapist over the years because of my parents.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;robin-hood-is-an-app-for-wall-street-bros&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#robin-hood-is-an-app-for-wall-street-bros&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: robin-hood-is-an-app-for-wall-street-bros&quot;&gt;Robin Hood is an app for Wall Street Bros&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole lose your job, and immediately become destitute is the reason why some countries have strong social safety nets.
We here in the US do not.
Whether we should or not is certainly something people will debate, but I won&#x27;t debate it here.
Instead I&#x27;ll just say, whereever you stand on the issue, we&#x27;re unlikely to all be able to quit our jobs with government help in the next few years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;its-a-free-country&#x2F;shove-it.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The album cover for Johnny Paycheck&amp;#39;s Take This Job and Shove It&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ol&#x27; Johnny&#x27;s gonna have to save up for a year or two before singing this one these days&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in order to combat the gap between Bezos&#x27; 50%, and you not being able to buy groceries if he fires you, it&#x27;s worth trying to figure something else out.
For pretty much anyone whose ever had to supplement their income, we already know what that something is: you get a second job.
You know what sucks?
Getting a second job.
Let&#x27;s see if we can make it a little better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;80000hours.org&#x2F;career-guide&#x2F;job-satisfaction&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this article from 80k hours&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; gives a nice overview of what to look for in a job.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that&#x27;s engaging&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that helps others&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work you&#x27;re good at&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with supportive colleagues&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that doesn&#x27;t have major negatives&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that fits with the rest of your life&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I don&#x27;t know about you, but that sounds like doing whatever it is you do with your friends to me.
I wonder if there&#x27;s something we could be doing to get paid there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every summer Games Done Quick puts on a week long marathon of video game speed runs.
There is a t-shirt company called The Yetee specializing in video game and fantasy-themed apparel.
Throughout the marathon they make sizable donations to support the runners, and the group they&#x27;re raising money for which is typically Doctors Without Borders.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those donations are marketing of course, but I&#x27;d rather $10k go to Doctors Without Borders than Zuckerberg&#x27;s island ruination fund.
Now we have a nice little loop: The Yetee donates to market -&amp;gt; speed runners volunteer their time to give this platform -&amp;gt; people buy from The Yetee -&amp;gt; repeat.
The platform is what makes the big donation worthwhile at a marketing tool.
But what if we didn&#x27;t need the platform?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole ecosystem of this speed running marathon is repeated all over the Earth in the hobbies and passions that we share with our friends.
They are what&#x27;s engaging, and what we&#x27;re good at, and by golly when you tell someone to purchase some super esoteric piece of essential paraphenelia, you should get a buck or two if they buy it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;its-a-free-country&#x2F;raccoon.png.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A statue of a raccoon drinking a bottle of beer&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;This bad boy retails for twelve hundred dollars. If you know why, and can articulate that to someone who buys it, I feel like you should get a cut.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mr-wonderful&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#mr-wonderful&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: mr-wonderful&quot;&gt;Mr. Wonderful&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve never seen Shark Tank, it&#x27;s a show where entrepreneurs get to go in front of a panel of five investors, and pitch them their idea.
For someone who loves watching ideas get pitched, it&#x27;s great even if the egregious percentages requested by the investors earns the show its name.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central investor of the show is Kevin O&#x27;Leary, aka Mr. Wonderful, who is well known for pitching fledgling entrepreneurs on royalty deals.
In the early seasons these deals were pretty rightly mocked by the other sharks, but as they, and the entrepreneurs, realized what Shark Tank really is (a giant marketing vehicle), and thus who they are as the &quot;sharks&quot; (influencers), the deals made more sense.
What&#x27;s the difference between paying Mr. Wonderful and Google a quarter for every sale?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cnbc.com&#x2F;2023&#x2F;09&#x2F;20&#x2F;more-than-half-of-gen-zers-think-they-can-easily-make-a-career-in-influencing.html&quot;&gt;2023 report from Morning Consult&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; found that 57% of gen Z wants to be influencers.
We have all sorts of words for the artifacts of this stuff, short-form content, reels, tiktoks, blah blah blah.
It&#x27;s all media.
When I was gen Z&#x27;s age, everyone wanted to be in a band, and it wasn&#x27;t just for the love of song.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look back at that list of what people want to do for a job:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that&#x27;s engaging&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that helps others&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work you&#x27;re good at&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with supportive colleagues&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that doesn&#x27;t have major negatives&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that fits with the rest of your life&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best things we did when I was in my band (we were not serious. We &lt;em&gt;were&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; drunk.) was make shower curtains for merch.
They were hysterical, and we sold out of them in minutes.
And we donated all the proceeds to a worthy cause: buying beer at our next practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn&#x27;t before the internet, but it was before the SoMa apps ruined it.
Could we have sold more shower curtains than we did?
Maybe, but that would&#x27;ve required paying for advertising because how else would anyone find out about them?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the hypothetical today: the band and I hop online and drop a grand on ad spend, and that gets spread amongst content creators.
We find that our shower curtains make more money than the mediocre slop rock we play, and pivot to grow our fledgling shower curtain empire.
Next thing you know, we&#x27;re on Shark Tank talking about how our Customer Acquisition Cost is $3.37 and Mr. Wonderful&#x27;s trying to sell us on a royalty so he can bestow upon us his brand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s sold as a win&#x2F;win.
He makes money when we make money.
You watch the ep, and tell a friend about it, and that person goes off and buys one of our shower curtains...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don&#x27;t you make money?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all do that all the time with our friends and families.
Recommendations, opinions, enthusiastic suggestions, this isn&#x27;t an anti-capitalist screed, we all buy stuff all the time, and we rely on these things from others to point us in the right direction.
So why do none of us get paid for that?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1984-man-you-were-right-that-s-a-typo&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1984-man-you-were-right-that-s-a-typo&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: 1984-man-you-were-right-that-s-a-typo&quot;&gt;&quot;1984 man, you were right, that&#x27;s a typo&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the dastardly answer to that question is that you have been.
The advertising aparatuses that generate this buzz, and associates your legwork with their products is giving you free software &lt;del&gt;to steal your personal information&lt;&#x2F;del&gt; for your enjoyment.
Google gives you free email, Meta free anxiety, Amazon close to free shipping, and all you have to give them is all of your browsing habits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, what you do with your time, online or otherwise, is your &quot;brand,&quot; and just like Mr. Wonderful, you should be compensated for it.
Just because your 32 followers are composed primarily of the birdwatching group you joined briefly five summers ago to have an excuse to get out of the house, doesn&#x27;t mean you shouldn&#x27;t get a dollar if someone buys the bird shirt you just saw somewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start putting this all together, you might ask, might it be possible to create a company that did tech-like things, and paid people royalties with every purchase?
You might then call up your lawyer, and layout this grand plan.
And then you get to watch him spread his arms once again, and remind you, &quot;Of course! It&#x27;s a free country.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool.
Now what&#x27;s interesting about paying people when they help sell something is you no longer have to spy on them to try to figure out what they want.
So we get to kill two gigantocorp bedrocks with one stone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about the free software and stuff?
Well, us programmers are weird.
Our field is very highly paid, but quite a few of us are quite happy programming things we like for free.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing I like is ripping the system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-simple-it-just-might-work-then-we-ll-quit-our-jobs&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#so-simple-it-just-might-work-then-we-ll-quit-our-jobs&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: so-simple-it-just-might-work-then-we-ll-quit-our-jobs&quot;&gt;&quot;So simple it just might work. Then we&#x27;ll quit our jobs.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#x27;s the whole idea in a nutshell.
People who sell things on the internet allow their things to be sold on this platform, which is non-exclusive, and requires minimal effort.
You all become independent contractors who get paid whenever a sale is made that you had a hand in.
Me, and a group of open source developers, provide the software that makes all this work for free.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a new word the other day: reciprocity.
Well to be fair I knew the word, but I learned it in a new context where it refers to a kind of sustainable economic loop where the outputs of one transaction are used as the inputs for a second, which then outputs back to the first.
I&#x27;m relatively certain that the coiners of the term would bristle at its usage with tech platforms, but the class war necessitates some linguistic casualties.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the value you bring to these transactions is extracted from you and monetized by the gigantocorps.
I want to pay you for that value.
(We didn&#x27;t really get into it, but these transactions run through &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;planet-nine-app&#x2F;planet-nine&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;FOSSialism.md&quot;&gt;infrastructure housed in cool spaces&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that you can help monetize too).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s like a big biodome, but instead of a biome, its binary.
A binaridome if you will.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this stuff is doable, it just takes one thing: people not being greedy dickheads.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d like to invite y&#x27;all to not be greedy dickheads with me.
It&#x27;d be your second job (or third or fourth, I don&#x27;t know your story), you can even put it on your LinkedIn&#x2F;resume--influencer, content marketer, philosophizer--doesn&#x27;t matter to me, I&#x27;ll vouch for you.
And all the money I make on this stuff, minus what I need to put my kid through college and retire at some point, I&#x27;ll turn around and pay out to you as royalties for being yourself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because at the end of the day, the notion that someone should own 50% of a company that many people have worked hard to build only makes sense to entitled psychopaths.
And now those dickheads want to be kings.
So we&#x27;re gonna have to get a little state motto of Virginia, or be ready for prima nocta shenanigans.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lfg&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#lfg&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: lfg&quot;&gt;LFG&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m going to outline how this works in the next post.
But I want to introduce the new Planet Nine logo here.
When you see this guy on something around cyberspace it means that someone is trying to be cool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, all of this nonsense wasn&#x27;t built in a day.
It&#x27;s not going to be undone in a day either.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But trust me when I say, I&#x27;m going to do my damnedest to make it fun to try.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Where&#x27;s your band</title>
        <published>2025-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/wheres-your-band/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/wheres-your-band/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/wheres-your-band/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;from the desk of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.planetnineisaspaceship.com&quot;&gt;planetnineisaspaceship&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-s-your-band&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#where-s-your-band&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: where-s-your-band&quot;&gt;Where&#x27;s your band&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a gorgeous fall evening in Skokie, Illinois.
Crisp and cool, the type of weather that my West Coast friends would call frigid today, but was just right for those of us in Chicago who wore hoodies year round.
I was standing outside in a huddle of teenagers smoking in between bands at the house show going on in my friend&#x27;s basement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Man, that last band really sucked.&quot;
It wasn&#x27;t my most eloquent critique of an artistic endeavor, and one probably more borne out of a need to be an angry teen than comment on the aesthetics of the show.
Next to me, a guy spun around.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Where&#x27;s your band man?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was older, probably nineteen or twenty, an unfathomable four year gap to my sixteen year old sensibilities.
I&#x27;m in my fourties now as I write this, and that his admonishment has stayed with me this long is a good indication he was on to something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#some-history&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: some-history&quot;&gt;Some history&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, the cultural vanguard that is The Simpsons released &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Guess_Who%27s_Coming_to_Criticize_Dinner%3F&quot;&gt;Guess Who&#x27;s Coming to Criticize Dinner&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
In the episode, Homer becomes a food critic who is first terrible at his job because he loves everywhere, and then is bad at his job because he needlessly criticizes everything.
I&#x27;d be curious to know what Gen Z thinks of the episode as one of the casualties of our increasingly online world is the professional critic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the internet, getting your opinion in front of more people than your friends required a gatekept platform monetized through circulation and&#x2F;or viewership numbers.
This meant that those who had opinions that would circulate were, for the most part, credentialed in whatever discipline it is they were critiquing.
One of the things that people who critique disciplines they&#x27;re a part of have, in general, is some respect for the craft--one that is shown as a modicum of respect for at least those who are trying.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2004, former PayPal execs (man those assholes seem to be behind everything stupid on the internet), launched Yelp.
Yelp had the novel idea of letting any Tom, Dick, and Harry with a keyboard write a review for any business regardless of any credentials.
The crowd-sourcing of critique is a fascinating and dynamic transition from expertise to democratization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether it&#x27;s been good, bad, or neutral is the topic of this post.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-band&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#my-band&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: my-band&quot;&gt;My band&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would, like five years later, start a band.
It was not entirely not to spite that dude at that house show.
It did, just as I suspect that guy knew, open my eyes to what he was talking about, and I&#x27;m thankful for the perspective.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, it is not the case that folks can&#x27;t or shouldn&#x27;t have opinions on the quality of any media they consume, of course they can.
It&#x27;s that deciding to get in front of any group of people and present something you&#x27;ve created is hard, and you don&#x27;t need some dickhead saying you suck right outside of the venue.
Sometimes showing appreciation for the craft is just keeping your mouth shut.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also demonstrated to me that getting on that stage is sometimes the end in itself.
Other people&#x27;s opinions aren&#x27;t really why you pick up the guitar.
I mean, maybe that&#x27;s it for some people, but it wasn&#x27;t for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;on-boiling-the-ocean&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Doing things for the sake of doing them is the subject of this other post.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;follow-the-money&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#follow-the-money&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: follow-the-money&quot;&gt;Follow the money&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve ever read anything else that I&#x27;ve written then you know that my main axe to grind is with internet monetization, and the &quot;democratization&quot; of reviews is no exception.
So let&#x27;s dive in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene Siskel and Roger Ebert were the popular film critics of the rival newspapers the Chicago Tribune, and the Chicago Sun-Times respectively.
Together they hosted a weekly film critic show on PBS when I was a kid.
It was a brilliant move of coopetition as their show likely upped circulation numbers for both newspapers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newspapers, and public broadcasting revenues are both driven by circulation&#x2F;viewership.
The more people consuming the media, the more revenue.
This incentives a quality show, and quality columns from both Siskel and Ebert.
The two of them rose to cultural prominence for America&#x27;s number two cultural export (music&#x27;s number one).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yelp, on the other hand, is a discovery tool just like a search engine.
Here&#x27;s what happens when I search for burrito on Yelp:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;wheres-your-band&#x2F;yelp.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yelp&amp;#39;s front page for searching burrito&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awesome.
I was in the mood for some Taco Bell when I went searching for burritos in one of the best food cities in the country.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was gonna checkout what&#x27;s after this row of sponsored things, and say at least that was good, but guess what.
It&#x27;s more ads.
One for a burger place.
Another for Top Golf.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously fuck this shit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-demos&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-demos&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-demos&quot;&gt;The Demos&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summer of 1997, I watched every movie that came out in theaters.
I lived across the street from a movie theater, I didn&#x27;t own a car, and the girls didn&#x27;t go to the pool every day so I had to fill my time with something.
I don&#x27;t remember all of the movies I watched, but I do remember I walked out of one, the only movie I&#x27;ve ever walked out of: Good Burger.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt of Roger Ebert&#x27;s review of Good Burger:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good Burger was not made for me, and if I say I didnt much enjoy it, that wouldnt be useful information. The movie was made for daytime viewers of Nickelodeon, and its a spinoff from a character first seen in the cable channels All That comedy seriesEd, a fast-food worker whose life and dreams are dominated by his love for his work, and whose catchphrase, Welcome to Good Burger, is as well-known to kids as Wheres the beef? is at the other end of the age spectrum.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent.
If I had read that, I probably would have skipped the movie.
It wasn&#x27;t that it was terrible, it was just for a much younger audience.
One that I might be able to appreciate now as a father, but that just didn&#x27;t do it for me as a teenager.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the review I just pulled up from the crowdsourcing on rotten tomatoes:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This movie is fantastic. The character are fun, and like silly, Ed and his friendship with Dex was great, Ed was funny, and this movie is so funny, one of the best comedy films of all time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really Conor S.?
One of the best of all time?
I&#x27;m going to need to see that list.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-s-conor-s&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#who-s-conor-s&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: who-s-conor-s&quot;&gt;Who&#x27;s Conor S.?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re unfamiliar with digital identity, and don&#x27;t want to read my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you-are-not-a-number&#x2F;&quot;&gt;15 part masterpiece on the subject&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, let me give you the tl;dr: Conor S. may not exist as you imagine him.
Perhaps you read his review, and concluded he was a well-intentioned internet denizen with questionable taste in cinema, and perhaps a particular taste for plants.
But since this is an unverified account on the internet, he could be a she, or an overworked and underpaid worker from a country lacking labor laws, or in this day of large language models he could even be another computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could even train a machine to believe Good Burger is in fact one of the best comedy films of all time so that for the machine, this review is objectively true.
How&#x27;s that Philosophy of Aesthetics professors!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rotten Tomatoes seems rather innocuous as far as spurious reviews are concerned, but what about Yelp, and Google?
What incentive do either of those platforms have to display or highlight reviews from establishments that aren&#x27;t paying them money?
Why do we trust, implicitly, the &quot;crowd sourced&quot; &quot;analysis&quot; of platforms whose whole design is pay-to-play?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-we-ever-care-though&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#did-we-ever-care-though&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: did-we-ever-care-though&quot;&gt;Did we ever care though?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in those days of going to shows in Chicago, there was perhaps the greatest all ages venue of all time in the Fireside Bowl.
America&#x27;s puritanical past enforces strict limitations on minors&#x27; ability to interface with alcohol with one notable exception: event spaces.
Without this exception, your first baseball game would be at 21, and wouldn&#x27;t hit quite the same way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a history I don&#x27;t care to look up, there was one kind of establishment in Chicago zoned like a stadium that wasn&#x27;t a stadium, the bowling alley.
Thanks to this zoning, the Fireside Bowl was able to supply concerts to rockers of all ages, and alcohol to those that the laws of the land allowed, and thus this venue of legend was born.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a show that if you were there is certainly etched in your memory.
The penultimate band was a local group called Wolfeyes, and the headliner was a two piece no one had heard before called Lightning Bolt.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember standing about a quarter of the way back from the stage vividly as the last chord of Wolfeyes set faded away, and was immediately cut into by the grinding dissonance that only a live show cranked up too loud can give you.
Everyone in the crowd turned around to see Lightning Bolt.
One member behind a tattered bass guitar with one guitar string that was already polluting the air with the fury fitting their name, the other member bent in half atop a full-stack plus of monitors and speakers.
Once enough eyes were on him, he lept down to the drum throne waiting for him and joined the noise in perfect time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sold all their merch that night, and more online I&#x27;m sure, and their next show in town sold out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m pretty sure they didn&#x27;t buy any ads.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scale of aggregation that the internet allows gives a skewed view of what a decision point is, and how it should be made.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Should I go see the Lightning Bolt?&quot;
&quot;Yes.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Should I get Taco Bell when I want a burrito?&quot;
Yelp says yes.
What do you say?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did we ever really care what Ebert had to say about a movie?
Maybe, but that was easily overridden by the people whose opinion we really care about, our family and friends.
Not only do we trust their opinion, but they know our preferences--I can gaurantee you no one that knows me is recommending Taco Bell, and Yelp is tapped into multiple spyware conglomorates I&#x27;m sure so it should know better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;word-of-mouth-is-king&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#word-of-mouth-is-king&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: word-of-mouth-is-king&quot;&gt;Word of mouth is king&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketers all over will tell you there is no substitute for word of mouth.
It&#x27;s fundamentally where recommendations come from.
If they came from random reviews on the internet then &lt;em&gt;that&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; would be monetized, and not the ads that supplant them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why not incentivize that?
Why not let people add themselves to a transaction pipeline where they get a little piece of recommending things to their family and friends?
Because then if they get too noisy with their recommendations, you can tell them to shut up lol...unlike ads on the internet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if they have the temerity of forming an opinion on something they don&#x27;t have the credentials to warrant, you can ask them, &quot;where&#x27;s your band?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>You are not a number</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you-are-not-a-number/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you-are-not-a-number/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you-are-not-a-number/">&lt;p&gt;Join planetnineisaspaceship as he takes you on a ride back through time on how we got from, &quot;Mr. Watson come here&quot; to a global network of spyware dehumanizing us all, and infiltrating all aspects of our every day life.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what we can do about it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;leave it to planet to write a &lt;strong&gt;15 part&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; screed on digital identity--ain&#x27;t nobody got time for that&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gaurantee you the parts are short and fun, but if you are indeed pressed for time, just read&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-12&quot;&gt;part 12 - The First Charge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-15&quot;&gt;part 15 - You&#x27;re invited&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-1&quot;&gt;part 1 - You are not a number&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An intro to the topic of digital identity, and how everyone has become just a set of eyeballs to market to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&quot;&gt;part 2 - The twentieth century&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AT&amp;amp;T does what gigantocorps do best&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-3&quot;&gt;part 3 - Out of the ashes&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dotcom bubble bursting gives way to totally less risky ventures&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-4&quot;&gt;part 4 - Looking for my space&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social media sites appear on the scene&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-5&quot;&gt;part 5 - Aristophones was right&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cloud appears to make store your data in the same place where you do all your shopping&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-6&quot;&gt;part 6 - It sure does rhyme&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven years after the dotcom bubble, the banks muck it up even worse&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-7&quot;&gt;part 7 - At least you&#x27;ve got the same rights as money&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sigh...Citizen&#x27;s United&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-8&quot;&gt;part 8 - The cell saga&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s how they know where you are&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-9&quot;&gt;part 9 - Are you entertained&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How they got into your TV&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-10&quot;&gt;part 10 - Data dreams by algorhythmics soundds pretty boring&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s talk about &quot;The Algorithm&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-11&quot;&gt;part 11 - Then there were nazis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Elwood and Jake, I hate nazis&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-12&quot;&gt;part 12 - The First Charge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How we can start reclaiming ourselves online&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-13&quot;&gt;part 13 - The third place&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-14&quot;&gt;part 14 - This part deals with internet denizens&#x27; proclivity for posting nudity online. If this makes you uncomfortable, feel free to skip it.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to deal with bad actors&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-15&quot;&gt;part 15 - You&#x27;re invited&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a boat...all you&#x27;ve got to do is hop aboard&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 1 - You are not a number</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-1/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-1/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-1&#x2F;.&#x2F;numbers.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Some of the numbers you are known by like phone number&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started college in 2000.
There were a few mobile phones in the US back then (they were much more prevalent across the Pacific at that time), mostly in cars.
I still remember the giant magnetized antenna that we plopped on top of our car just in case my parents needed to make a call on the side of the road.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#x27;t have a car though, nor did I have a phone.
I received calls like most of the rest of my dorm on a single handset hung from the wall, and dispatched to from the school&#x27;s switchboard.
The phone would ring, someone would pick it up, and then shout out through the halls for whomever was supposed to answer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing weird there at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set up in 2000 just so happened to overlap with the advent of loyalty programs in retailers.
To this day, I reckon you could probably take the main phone number of every college and university in the US, and use it to invoke any loyalty program at a retailer that was around back in 2000.
I still use my school&#x27;s number from time to time, and it always works.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I did get my first cell phone, I picked up a number in the 312 area of downtown Chicago because it was, and is cool.
I will hold on to that number for all time.
I do not want to share it with Krogers and Piggly-Wigglies, and I don&#x27;t need to be texted thirty times a day &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Facebook,_Inc._v._Duguid&quot;&gt;because Facebook didn&#x27;t want to pay some poor guy $10k for pestering him&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I want instead is to use my alma mater&#x27;s number for everything, and leave my cool number for my cool friends.
But all those darn &#x27;puters need me to be &quot;me&quot; so they send me a text for verification, and that can&#x27;t go to that handset on the wall, and I don&#x27;t live there anymore anyways so it doesn&#x27;t work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-are-not-a-handle&quot;&gt;You are not a handle&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was maybe twelve or thirteen I &quot;invented&quot; a mythology.
I guess to go back even further, when I was in grammar school, I exhausted the school library&#x27;s entries on mythology.
Pantheons, and the stories they create have been one of my many obsessions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mythology was the pantheon of the Ephesians, a group I only knew existed from random bible passages since Wikipedia had not been invented yet.
It included maybe twelve gods and goddesses, which fit into the sophisticated mind of a boy in the midst of puberty.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only remember a few, like Betedoun, the Ephesian god of war.
He was responsible for sending a meteor to kill the dinosaurs, because he didn&#x27;t think they were cool enough iirc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader of this divine group was Ramdatookisodom, Ephesian god of sexual tendencies.
Before you ask, yes this name purposefully contains two not-so-veiled references to anal sex.
To twelve year old Catholic me, some pagan deity tappin&#x27; everything around him was about as iconclastic as I could get. And since the Greeks&#x27; Zeus had already filled the role of banging everything that moves for procreation, I had to get a little creative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was right around this time that my Dad got us a Compuserve account, and I started going online.
Stranger Danger being a thing even before the internet, I somehow had enough sense not to use my real name online, so when I had to identify myself, I used the name of one of my creations: Ramdatooki.
How&#x27;s that for dodging the vulgarity filters :tap-forehead:.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later when it became time to start getting in touch with colleges, I made the grown up decision to retire Ramdatooki as my handle, and update to something more sophisticated: zkpunk @ hotmail.com.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then gmail burst on the scene, and they nailed the false demand created by artificial constraint by keeping their service invite-only for years.
Through some connections to the more 31337 parts of the internet (4chan) I was able to score an invite, and secured the coveted firstnamelastname @ gmail.com.
Afaict there is only one other Zach Babb, and him and I seem to be around the same age, and we compete for signing up first for things.
It&#x27;s a friendly competition for me.
I hope he feels the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the socials came, where it mattered who you were to some (Facebook), and to others you could be pseudonymous (Twitter and Reddit).
Handles proliferated so much that services created just to link to your online personas were created and actually monetizable (according to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.adamenfroy.com&#x2F;linktree-alternatives&quot;&gt;this&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; there are at least sixteen of these services around).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So who am I?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramdatooki, Zweibel (the german word for onion, but before I knew that I named myself after &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theonion.com&#x2F;t-herman-zweibel-in-memoriam-1819583647&#x2F;&quot;&gt;T. Herman Zweibel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), zkpunk, zachbabb at gmail&#x2F;me&#x2F;mac&#x2F;icloud, zach at planetine&#x2F;zkbabb, CurvatureTensor, planetnineisaspaceship...?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are you?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&quot;&gt;Continue on to part 2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 10 - Data dreams by algorhythmics sounds pretty boring</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-10/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-10/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-10/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1984-was-a-typo&quot;&gt;1984 was a typo&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2014, the tech giant advertisers had the apparatus in place to effectively spy on everyone everywhere that a machine connected to other machines. Anything done digitally more or less anywhere on Earth was collected, processed, and sold.
And out of their benevolence they used this information to create, and rapidly deliver, an unprecedented decade of creativity and techno-social progress never before seen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s what happened right?&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#9&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
I mean, at least we got airpods...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well if these assholes weren&#x27;t making things that people wanted, what the heck were they doing?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-algorithm&quot;&gt;The algorithm&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember those math class games in grade school where&#x27;d you pick a number, and then do some math, and it&#x27;d always come out to the same number regardless of what you picked?
Claude tells me this is a classic one:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick any number (1-99)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add 7&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiply by 2&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subtract 4&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divide by 2&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subtract your original number&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will always come out to five.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get to college and take some computer science courses, eventually you come across algorithms.
Like many computer science terms, there isn&#x27;t a singular exact definition of what an algorithm is, but it&#x27;s more or less this math game.
There is some number of steps that take some input, and always produces the same output.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has long been known that content displayed to users on social media platforms can change based on the user&#x27;s behavior and likes and dislikes.
In the past few years people have been talking about The Algorithm, as in the underlying process by which these platforms choose to display you content.
Whether it&#x27;s a singular algorithm, or an amalgamation is immaterial.
But what it&#x27;s trying to do isn&#x27;t.
Let&#x27;s see if we can figure that out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems reasonable.
How about this?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage them to invite their friends&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show their friends content that they all like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&#x27;s just hanging with their friends having a good time&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok cool, everything seems good here, but of course eventually you&#x27;re going to have to pay the servers hosting all of this content.
So you monetize:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in some ads, but not too many&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage them to invite their friends&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show their friends content that they all like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in some ads, but not too many&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&#x27;s just hanging with their friends having a good time&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, usage growth stalls, competition moves in, but shareholders need that growth. So you start messing with The Algorithm to get the results you want.
Eventually, the ads are the purpose of the algorithm:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage them to invite their friends&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show their friends content that they all like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&#x27;s just hanging with their friends having a good time&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep people watching AAAADDDDDSSSSS!!!!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing to see here, just some good ol&#x27; fashioned capitalism right?
But then they hire an intern who goes ahead and makes just one tiny tweak to The Algorithm, see if you can catch it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage them to invite their friends&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show their friends content that they all like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&#x27;s just hanging with their friends having a good time&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep people watching political AAAADDDDDSSSSS!!!!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you catch it?
Some folks didn&#x27;t.
How about a few months later when that intern goes ahead and sprinkles their flavoring a bit more:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn about a user&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show them political content they like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They return to your platform because its nice&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage them to invite their friends&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show their friends political content that they all like&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in lots of ads&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&#x27;s just hanging with their friends having a good time&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep people watching political AAAADDDDDSSSSS!!!!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-10&#x2F;.&#x2F;simpsons.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screen grab from the Simpsons when one festival goer asks, &amp;quot;are you being sarcastic dude?&amp;quot; and the other goes, &amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t even know anymore,&amp;quot; but instead of &amp;quot;sarcastic&amp;quot; it says &amp;quot;political&amp;quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the problem with this algorithm is that it comes down to whether you agree with the intern or not.
And that&#x27;s what makes undoing this shit so hard, because the whole algorithm is designed to make you feel good when you are aligned with it.
So when someone who you perceive as being different from you comes for your darlings saying they&#x27;re poisoned, it causes defensiveness, and fear.
The sides become entrenched, and the surveilance apparatus grows in power.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#x27;s why we&#x27;re not going to try to do it that way.
Instead, I hope that regardless of political affiliation, and your take on the necessity of surveilance in the rule of law, we can agree that with respect to corporations, people should always have the option to opt out.
Opting out&#x27;s just such a gnarly mess, that we have to get creative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-11&quot;&gt;Continue to part 11&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These jamokes reneged on so many dumb promises during this time, but the one that I think just really sums it all up is Haven, the healthcare venture that Warren Buffet and Jeff Bezos started to fix healthcare. It shutdown unceremoniously in 2021, after doing nothing. The second richest man on Earth just gives up after a couple of years, because something&#x27;s too hard, what a ballsack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 11 - Then there were nazis</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-11/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-11/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-11/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;every-party-s-a-just-a-party-until-there-re-nazis-then-it-s-a-nazi-party&quot;&gt;Every party&#x27;s a just a party until there&#x27;re nazis--then it&#x27;s a nazi party&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-frontlines&quot;&gt;The frontlines&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the EU passed the first real protections against the incredible spying apparatus the internet had become.
Probably the most noticable thing it did from a day-to-day perspective is that it makes websites which use cookies to track you have to disclose that they do so, and make them opt-in.
How many of y&#x27;all know how that works, and what you should opt-in to?
How many of you care to learn?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll give you two guesses as to who the biggest provider of cookie-based tracking is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here&#x27;s how that tracking works.
Google and Meta each give you a number.
Every time you log in to anything anywhere, you&#x27;re given another number.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Google and Meta spend billions and billions of dollars making sure that they can tie the second number to the first.
Then that first number is given some set of lifetime-values: the amount of money you&#x27;re likely to spend based on your demographics, and your personality, all of which they know because they&#x27;ve been spying on you since the first time your mouse clicked login.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And somewhere, deep in the bowels of a network you&#x27;re not invited to, they&#x27;ve added those two numbers together, and probably handed it off to all the governments that they regularly break the regulations of with impunity.
I don&#x27;t know what this number looks like, but in computers we have these things called universal unique identifiers (UUIDs), and they look like this: C6B20666-6AF4-4DF6-AB57-8F47A429D415.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#x27;s what you and I are: C6B20666-6AF4-4DF6-AB57-8F47A429D415, just a hexadecimal number, followed around the internet by the largest corporations the Earth has ever known.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-11&#x2F;.&#x2F;apps.svg&quot; alt=&quot;An svg of the following privacy-focused apps&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against this there are browsers blocking trackers like Firefox and even Safari, browser extensions fighting back like Privacy Badger and ClearURLs, platforms like signal and matrix for messaging, ad blockers like UBlock, DuckDuckGo for search, Protonmail for email, OpenStreetMap for maps, self-hosted cloud apps you can run in your house.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the projects on the frontlines of this battle.
Please check them out and give them your support.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;fuckin-nazis&quot;&gt;Fuckin&#x27; nazis&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dad&#x27;s favorite movie is Patton.
The movie begins with the incomporable George C. Scott&#x27;s rendition of the titular general&#x27;s speech to the third army in advance of the allied invasion of France.
It&#x27;s a good speech.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=sv9XNFpRdhg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;img.youtube.com&#x2F;vi&#x2F;sv9XNFpRdhg&#x2F;0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Youtube video of the movie&amp;#39;s speech&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching it as a kid, one of those memories that&#x27;s not really continuous with anything else, just some moment you remember for some reason or another.
There&#x27;s a part where Scott&#x27;s Patton says, &quot;we&#x27;re going to hold them by the nose, and kick them in the ass!&quot; and my dad turned to me and said, &quot;that&#x27;s really what he did. His army would hold the front, and then attack the rear.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so when the richest man on Earth threw two nazi salutes up at the inauguration of the president that my dad tried to overthrow the government for it hit a bit personally.
My dad may have forgotten about the war that his dad fought in, but hearing about it left an impression on me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I figured what worked for Patton, might just work for me, and I got to work on the kick them in the ass part.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specifics of the work are far too much to go into here, but the gist of it is this: build a system that&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a) allows for monetization that isn&#x27;t ad-based&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;b) allow users to proliferate their digital identities&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;c) mess with existing notions of identity&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I&#x27;ll just ask that you take my word on a).
It&#x27;s obviously quite important, but again too big for here.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For b) we already know the model, but we have a lot more computing horsepower to go along with it.
You just bring back the handle--Ramdatooki, zweibel, and zkpunk can all live again.
And why don&#x27;t we throw in anonymity alongside pseudonymity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course websites aren&#x27;t just going to switch to handles overnight, and remembering which ones you used where is impossible, so what if we treated it like a password manager?
And what if we setup a mail server that gave everyone random site-by-site emails that did nothing other than confirm themselves when users signed up for and in to things?
And then, what if we just signed up a few extra users every time you went somewhere, and poked around at some things?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thinking about that, and c), what if we took all the accounts on social media that people are abandoning because of the nazi thing, and start handing them to people who turn them into zombie bots, and all of a sudden uuids like C6B20666-6AF4-4DF6-AB57-8F47A429D415 started being into different things?
What happens to the advertising platforms when all of the spying that they rely on suddenly becomes junk, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; because we undid 30 years and trillions of dollars worth of spying infrastructure, but because the numbers that they think we are just aren&#x27;t us anymore?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-12&quot;&gt;Continue to part 12&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching idea is to make it much easier for people to simply purchase things directly from created content. This actually isn&#x27;t as technically hard as you might think now in 2025, but it is difficult to explain because it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; different from how the internet works today. Once I write up that blog post, I&#x27;ll link it here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 12 - The First Charge</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-12/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-12/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-12/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-are-not-a-number&quot;&gt;You are not a number&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sixties Patrick McGoohan wrote, directed, and starred in an incredible 17 episode show called The Prisoner.
In it McGoohan plays a spy who attempts to retire, and for doing so is sent to a mysterious island as a prisoner.
The opening of the show always features a shadowy character named Number 2 who tells McGoohan that they need information, and that McGoohan is Number Six.
To this, McGoohan responds:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;I am not a number, I am a free man!&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=0a1_v-BJ-Wc&amp;amp;t=118&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;img.youtube.com&#x2F;vi&#x2F;0a1_v-BJ-Wc&#x2F;0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Youtube video of the opening of The Prisoner&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning human beings into numbers is a dehumanizing act akin to calling them animals or statistics.
It makes it easier to convince yourself that you&#x27;re doing the right thing, because there&#x27;s no way all those poeple are going to figure it out.
After all, they were dumb enough to become numbers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&#x27;d imagine that faced by some similarly nefarious captor dictating to us just what number we had to be, our reactions might be similar to McGoohan&#x27;s... unless we were actual prisoners where this is exactly what happens.
And at the risk of a reductio ad Hitler, let&#x27;s also remember how the nazis assigned numbers to Jewish people and members of other groups they wanted to extinguish.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-brief-aside-on-how-computers-work-and-how-we-can-t-get-rid-of-numbers-all-together&quot;&gt;A brief aside on how computers work, and how we can&#x27;t get rid of numbers all together&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so letters in computers are called chars, and an ordered group of chars is called a string.
These are represented inside of the computer as zeros and ones in a system called binary.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-12&#x2F;.&#x2F;binary.png&quot; alt=&quot;An image showing &amp;quot;hello world&amp;quot; in binary&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even that is an abstraction over high and low voltages within the actual circuitry of the chips in the computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so we could say that some computer representation of you was high-high-low-high, and try to convince people that that wasn&#x27;t a number, but then smart alecs would be like, &quot;oh yeah, but high and low are like five volts and zero volts so it&#x27;s still really a number.&quot;
And then all of this would devolve into some barroom discussion of the semantic metaphysics of Maxwell&#x27;s equations, and while that would be fun for a bit, we&#x27;d have lost sight of the fact that billionaires are counting us to get bogged down in semantics rather than revolting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can&#x27;t get totally away from numbers on computers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nothing-says-you-can-t-be-lots-of-numbers&quot;&gt;Nothing says you can&#x27;t be lots of numbers&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-green-lantern&quot;&gt;The Green Lantern&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first job out of high school was as a barista at Starbucks.
Being 19 years old, and having to work at five in the morning, wasn&#x27;t my favorite, but the coffee helped.
To maximize my ability to intake the coffee, because Howard Schultz forbade you take a second to drink some once the customers start coming in, I would mix hot coffee and iced coffee together.
To this day, I prefer my coffee luke warm, much to the horror of my wife, and probably you the reader.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lack of other prospects I stuck around with the company and worked my way up to manager.
The partners at my first store called my luke warm coffee a green lantern.
Because when you have a unique drink, that becomes your name at the store.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;lazer&quot;&gt;Lazer&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used to play punk rock softball on Wednesdays back then.
Chicago has a special breed, played barehanded with a sixteen inch ball.
We&#x27;d play 30 to a side, forties in hand, in parks around the city.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Athletic ability was not our forte, we were band and theater kids, not jocks, and for some reason I was one of the few people who could throw from third to first with accuracy.
One night I made a throw and someone (I remember who, but won&#x27;t dox him here) was like, &quot;damn dude, that was like a laser!&quot;
And from that night on, I was Lazer to that group.
There are still some people who only know me as that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;zachary&quot;&gt;Zachary&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many people would you say you&#x27;ve introduced yourself to?
Let&#x27;s call it a couple thousand.
For me most of those people know me as what I introduced myself as, Zach.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more than ten, but less than twenty people that know me as Zachary.
Sadly that number has dwindled as people have aged, and time has taken them.
It&#x27;s what my family calls me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who was I in my early twenties?
The professional Green Lantern, the wild partier Lazer, or Zachary--just some kid trying to find his way in the world?
Do we not all have these kind of personas?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And aren&#x27;t we all entitled to not have to share the antics of Lazer with our job and our family?
Anyone who&#x27;s been fired from a job, or trapped in a political polemic with a family member because of a Facebook post knows the answer to that one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;billions-and-billions&quot;&gt;Billions and billions&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re the type to hang around the interwebs and join things chances are you&#x27;ve had a password or two stolen, and dumped onto the dark web.
Maybe you&#x27;re already using a password manager because of that, or otherwise making sure passwords are unique across different logins.
What if we could do the same with email?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oho! You exclaim, I already know about adding a + to the end of the first part of my email and making new ones like zach+anotheremail@planetnine.app.
But that&#x27;s just an alias to your original email.
I&#x27;m talking about just a random new email that you never look at, or have to worry about.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know you can just like setup an email server, and give yourself names?
People don&#x27;t really do it that much because there&#x27;s all this bullshit that the big email providers (google) have added to make sure people don&#x27;t just get spammed all the time.
I&#x27;ll leave it to you to decide whether they&#x27;re succeeding at keeping the spam at bay, or simply ensuring they&#x27;re the only spam providers around.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thing is though, nothing is stopping you from &lt;em&gt;receiving&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; emails.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let me ask you this, when&#x27;s the last time you sent a jaunty personal email to a friend just for fun?
For the two people who said recently, does the email you used to do that need to be the same email you use to sign in to things?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How&#x27;s about the next thing you sign up for we use an email like: C6B20666-6AF4-4DF6-AB57-9F47A429D415@iamnotanumber.com?
Did you look up to see if this is the same uuid as before?
Does it matter?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what if even the domain proliferated so that sometimes you were @iamnotanumber.com, and sometimes you were @oligarchymorelikeolibarfy.com?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what if all this happened for free, and all you had to do was turn a browser extension on?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then maybe that random app free trial you signed up for can just go away rather than email you every other day to come back and subscribe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-my-phone-number&quot;&gt;What about my phone number?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you seen The Wire?
If you haven&#x27;t you should immediately stop reading this, and dedicate the next five seasons worth of tv you watch to the greatest show ever made.
If you have, you know just how easy it is to get burner phone numbers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&#x27;t your number that matters for the six numbers the website sends you, it&#x27;s the notion that that phone number is attached to a device that&#x27;s on your person at all times.
So long as we get that code to something that fits that bill then we&#x27;re good.
And again that&#x27;s the browser extension that gives you a burner number, and then fills in the code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least that&#x27;s the short-term solution.
Long-term, we become our own carrier with some kind of rotating number system that follows the law, and doesn&#x27;t get shared with gigantocorps.
But Rome wasn&#x27;t built in a day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-advancement-s-first-charge&quot;&gt;The Advancement&#x27;s first charge&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collective effort to undo the damage The Advertisement has wrought is called The Advancement, and this is its first charge.
&lt;em&gt;Proliferate&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; identities across cyberspace, and do so with something so easy to use, that all anyone has to do is install it.
You don&#x27;t have to lose the ability to be yourself, but you gain the ability to be whomever you want.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-creative&quot;&gt;Getting creative&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surprising amount of the way I interpret the world comes from playing the original Final Fantasy when I was like six or seven lol.
When you start that game, you select four characters, and you give them a name.
Your entry point into this world is this ontological decision about who you are, and who is coming along with you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-12&#x2F;.&#x2F;ff1.png&quot; alt=&quot;The first final fantasy&amp;#39;s character generation screen&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Fantasy fans will recognize the names here as four character representations of the series&#x27; final bosses. I&#x27;ll leave it to the fans to guess how to do the next one in four characters&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice acting ruined this subtle yet powerful notion.
&lt;em&gt;I&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; was no longer the protagonist in my game, and my party was no longer my friends.
I was just a passenger on a ride packaged up for me in design studios around the world--still fun to be sure, but missing just that little something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talked much earlier about handles, and how I&#x27;ve had different ones over the years.
In games like these I could have the same handle, and be different things.
Zach the fighter, Zach the paladin, and Zach the, ahem, treasure hunter, each had different incredible adventures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole of the digital realm I could be whomever or whatever I wanted.
Companies could give me structure to fit myself into, or some lack of structure to explore.
The notion that you had to be yourself was so anathema that you would never even dream of sharing personal information in some random chat room.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#x27;d drop into a chat room, get bombarded with &quot;asl,&quot; and only fools would actually drop the correct answers to those questions.
And in this way the creepy old men would self-select by &quot;being&quot; totally legal teen women who would go off together and have criminally unsatisfying lesbian cybersex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the rest of us who weren&#x27;t there because nudey pics still downloaded too slowly were the most interesting group of philosophers, scientists, inventors, artists, and writers ever assembled--it didn&#x27;t matter that in real life we were whatever we were, and we didn&#x27;t have to share our phone numbers to get there.
That&#x27;s what the internet&#x27;s for goshdarnit!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want this back.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-13&quot;&gt;Continue to part 13&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 13 - The third place</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-13/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-13/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-13/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-what-about-all-those-places-that-already-have-my-number&quot;&gt;But what about all those places that already have my number?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2008, I was working at the Apple Store on Michigan Avenue in Chicago when the iPhone 3G, and the App Store launched.
Back in those days, the iPhone only worked with AT&amp;amp;T, and so we had to port a lot of customers numbers over to that service.
To do so required a bunch of personal information from the account holder.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we were the only way to get these phones, our store served the plebes and elites alike, but if you were a big enough deal you could at least skip the line that wrapped around the block.
I handled a number of these special transactions, and it was after helping a very nice family get iPhones on their account where the account holder was a certain retired Bulls basketball player who might take it personally if I further reveal who he was, that I realized I was in the wrong business.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided then to go back to school.
It took two years to get all those ducks in a row, but in 2010, I sold or donated about 90% of my possesions, loaded the rest of everything I owned into my 2000 Camry, and moved out to Portland, OR. to go back to Reed College, the school I had done my freshman year at a decade earlier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving is scary.
Leaving our comfort zones, the people we know and love, our haunts, the places we feel safe, our &lt;em&gt;communities&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;...that&#x27;s scarier to most of us than even death.
It&#x27;s why back in the day exile, and excomunication were the real bad punishments.
At least with the iron maiden you died fairly quickly, and didn&#x27;t have to deal with the daily torment that people no longer wanted to be your friend.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online though you don&#x27;t have to leave, and go to a new place.
I lived through all my friends ditching Friendster for MySpace, and then MySpace for Facebook.
It was like that sad reminder that each one of us leaves the playground with our friends one last time, we just don&#x27;t know it then.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it didn&#x27;t have to be that way.
We don&#x27;t have to choose one or another.
That division is an &lt;em&gt;artificial separation created by companies looking to monetize your activity&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
What if the next time we all decide to move the next best thing, we require that thing to play nicely with others.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course we can&#x27;t just ditch the interwebs to go out into the world where things already play nicely with others.
Gore forbid we just ditch the internet and go touch grass or something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;did-you-or-did-you-not&quot;&gt;DID you, or DID you not?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one number we haven&#x27;t talked about yet used to identify people online.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DID stands for Distributed IDentifier.
It&#x27;s a way of assigning a canonical id to a user within a distributed system.
The most popular system using DIDs right now is Bluesky, where if you own your own domain you can set your DID in a DNS record and have your handle be handle@&amp;lt;your-domain.com&amp;gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A yoctosecond is 10^-24 seconds.
It&#x27;s used to describe the lifetime of really elusive particles.
It&#x27;s also about the time it took Meta and Google to connect your Bluesky DID to their uuids.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep trying to update the wikipedia page with this info, but someone keeps erasing it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, so long as distributed systems are trying to give you a single canonical identifier, the l337 coders at the gigantocorps will be linking them to their number for you, and serving you ads based on what you post on Bluesky.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fediverse&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#11&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; works in a similar way, but instead of giving you a canonical id for all of the Fediverse, your ids are stored in a server that is federated with the system.
That server is typically only linked to one of the Fediverse&#x27;s implementations, and so if you really really want to you can proliferate your identities across the Fediverse, but to do so you need different emails, and you need to connect to a bunch of different servers, and since this isn&#x27;t a common use case, none of the existing apps are built to do this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-13&#x2F;.&#x2F;fediverse.png&quot; alt=&quot;A diagram of the different implementations of the ActivityPub protocol, which is called The Fediverse&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear that I really like the Fediverse, and AT-protocol endeavors like Bluesky.
They are absolutely a step in the right direction, and if they were built now, I think they would have been more careful with how identity was handled.
As they exist, the protocols are set, and changing protocols is very difficult as ipv6, tls 1.3, and HTTP&#x2F;2 can attest to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to reward and monetize the content creators on these platforms for blazing the trail, but monetization is out of the scope of this doc.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#14&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-re-living-in-a-society&quot;&gt;We&#x27;re living in a society&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are social animals.
That&#x27;s the axiom of social media, but how social is social media today, and how much of it is just short quips of entertainment?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day in the car, after our son was born, my wife turned to me and said, &quot;I wish there was a place that adults could just like go, and hang out, and talk with each other, and maybe other adults. Away from kids you know?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chuckled and said, &quot;That&#x27;s called a bar babe. You just described a bar.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been to a lot of bars.
You know what makes a good bar?
People being there when you arrive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first it&#x27;s the bartender, so you get to know them.
Then it&#x27;s regulars.
Then you and your friends become regulars so you know one of y&#x27;all will be there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This worked before texting.
And it worked before the bar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summer break before eigth grade, I spent most of my days riding my bike to the pool.
That&#x27;s where my friends were.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it was the mall.
Then it was Pete&#x27;s garage.
Then it was Skippy&#x27;s house.
Then it was the gazebo.
Then it was Jack&#x27;s.
Then it was the Quad.
Then it was the Manor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These places are third places.
Your home is the first place, your job the second place, and your third place is where you go for your community.
Instagram is not your community.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s been much written about the loss of third places, including the sociological dynamo Bowling Alone, which was written about this and other losses in community back in 2000.
The general theme of these writings is that humans not congregating in person is leading to the crumbling and decay of society.
We&#x27;ve replaced the places we&#x27;d go to solve the world&#x27;s problems with places that&#x27;re the source of those problems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not here to tell you how to spend your spare time, but in trying to build something that could solve this identity problem, I felt it needed to have some sense of community to keep the feeling going.
The &quot;social graph,&quot; a meaningless term for the notion that people are connected to each other, isn&#x27;t possible when the computers don&#x27;t know who you are.
But online still needs its communities, so how do we do that?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;well-how-does-the-bar-work&quot;&gt;Well how does the bar work?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was working at Starbucks in my early twenties, I would hang out in this hip cozy cafe in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Flat_Iron_Building_(Chicago)&quot;&gt;Flat Iron building&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at the corner of Milwaukee, North, and Damen in Chicago&#x27;s Wicker Park--a neighborhood so cool, it spawned a movie.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a large cafe with maybe three or four sections.
I hung out in the cool upper level, which I knew was cool because I was there.
And up there I met the other upper level regulars, a fine group of men and women whose names I&#x27;ve forgotten.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is my life better or worse because I met these people before I had some way to save them in a database forever?
If somehow I found out there was a cafe reunion of some sorts would I go?
Life goes on you know?
Maybe we don&#x27;t need to carry around a record of every person we&#x27;ve ever talked to for more than two minutes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cafes and bars work because they&#x27;re there.
You can go to them or not.
If you keep going to them, they &lt;em&gt;become&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; your third place--the community&#x27;s built by the participants.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what if that was how social media worked?
What if instead of following people, and having to get people to follow you, you could &quot;go to&quot; places.
You like the place, you keep showing up and build the community.
You don&#x27;t like the place, you&#x27;re under no obligation to stay.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so now when you leave one of these platforms where you&#x27;ve sunk a decade into building followers, you&#x27;ve got followers already because they&#x27;re part of your &lt;em&gt;community&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t some far fetched dream, it&#x27;s how the whole internet worked before they decided you had to be &lt;em&gt;you&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; online.
If you wanted to see what shows were playing that weekend, you&#x27;d hop into some chatroom for your genre of choice in your locale, give yourself the handle musicdude22, and just ask.
People would just like tell you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then maybe you&#x27;d hang around for a while, chat about tunes, learn some new bands, and then log off.
Maybe you come back, maybe you don&#x27;t.
It doesn&#x27;t matter.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chatroom lives on, just sitting there to help the next audiophile find their next show.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-14&quot;&gt;Continue to part 14&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;11&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both The Fediverse, and Bluesky are implementations of distributed systems based on underlying protocols. The Fediverse&#x27;s ActivityPub protocol, and thus The Fediverse, came first, but despite the first-mover advantage, lags behind Bluesky these days in user adoption. The reason for this is a combo of marketing and usability, and definitely outside of the scope of this footnote.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;14&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I can&#x27;t completely leave out the money. The idea is to make it much easier to transact on the internet, using the existing financial system, by being able to purchase from user content directly instead of needing it to redirect you to a store.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 14 - This part deals with internet denizens proclivity for posting nudity online. If that makes you uncomfortable, feel free to skip it.</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-14/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-14/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-14/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-know-it-when-i-see-it&quot;&gt;I know it when I see it&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1964, supreme court justice Potter Stewart wrote,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shall not today attempt further to define the kinds of material I understand to be embraced within that shorthand description [regarding what is, and is not pornography]; and perhaps I could never succeed in intelligibly doing so. But I know it when I see it, and the motion picture involved in this case is not that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case concerns the showing of a French film, Les Amants (The Lovers), the parent&#x27;s guide for this smutty offering on IMDB is the following:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot of this film revolves around a married woman&#x27;s unhappiness with her marriage and her subsequent affairs with other men. One of these affairs becomes sexual within the plot of the film, and we see the couple kiss passionately while laying on a boat on a lake. There is a subsequent scene in which the two make love. While the sex is not shown explicitly, we do see breast nudity and from the erotic nature of the scene it is clear that both people are enjoying their lovemaking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most scandalous part of this is probably the depiction of a woman enjoying her love making.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the government&#x27;s standards of obscenity is one thing, and though this case was brought about due to the puritanism of Ohioans in the 1960s, I don&#x27;t necessarily begrudge them setting their own standards for what is and what is not ok.
The case was appealed to the US Supreme Court where The Constitution superceded the states&#x27; laws, and the system worked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people who dive into anonymity in online identities tout themselves as first amendment purists, letting nazis and smut peddlers alike hang out as equals with everyone else.
Those of you still on Twitter may have noticed this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not of that opinion--and while we&#x27;re at it, neither is the US Federal Government.
Here are ten things the US government doesn&#x27;t consider free speech:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-14&#x2F;.&#x2F;not-free-speech.png&quot; alt=&quot;The ten things are obscenity, child pornography, yelling &amp;quot;fire!&amp;quot;, fighting words, libel, comments made while holding an occupation, burning draft cards, school newspapers, endorsing candidates as a religious person, and speaking in public&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the US government isn&#x27;t the government of the world, and these things aren&#x27;t always defined, and some of them, like fighting words, take on different meanings in online contexts.
But ignoring the legal nuance, the real question is, should you try and enforce some restriction on what people say and post, how do you do that when people are anonymous?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media platforms where your profile is who you are, and you have some sunk cost wrapped up in gained followers, getting banned matters.
But on a platform where you can just spawn accounts at will, and reach people through some community space, what&#x27;s the equivalent of a ban?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than get bogged down on what is, and what isn&#x27;t obscene, we&#x27;ll move forward by talking about dicks.
Why? Because left to their own devices, dick-havers will put those things everywhere.
So below as I say dicks, feel free to fill in the details of whatever lewd or illegal material you care more about.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not putting a picture of a dick onto the internet in some capacity is illegal, is a matter of locale, but the requirement that others should have to &lt;em&gt;view&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that dick is a matter of personal preference.
So the goal is to create an anonymous platform that can handle both user preference for dicks, and some sort of excommunication for those who post dicks in places where it&#x27;s illegal to do so.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#12&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most social platforms allow for the opting in of NSFW content, and that seems like a good place to start.
But that requires moderation since not everyone will add that flag to their NSFW content.
For our implementations, users will be able to add that tag, amongst others, so that people can filter out NSFW content without mod intervention.
Tagging lets us get more specific as some people might want to see dicks, but not other sex organs, or other sex organs, and not dicks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter is a little trickier, and I&#x27;ve given it a lot of thought, and I don&#x27;t really know how else to do it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to upload things, you&#x27;ve got to make a purchase.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-you-in-compliance&quot;&gt;Are you in compliance?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the early eighties, it became pretty obvious that transacting online was going to be a thing.
When the world wide web went live in the mid-nineties, online eCommerce sites suddenly saw an explosion in the number of customers they could reach, and, as a result of the loosey-goosey security at the time, the credit card networks were nearing a billion dollars in fraud.
To combat this, the payments industry created the Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI DSS).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re big enough for the credit card companies to care about, and you&#x27;re found to not be in PCI compliance, they&#x27;ll drop you and&#x2F;or your payment processor will drop you, and you won&#x27;t be able to take transactions anymore.
When there&#x27;s money involved, it&#x27;s easy to ban people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things PCI compliance requires is that eCommerce sites not store people&#x27;s credit card numbers anywhere.
Instead, these numbers are tokenized, and stored to be resolved at time of purchase by the payment processors.
This means that your details are anonymized to the eCommerce site, but the banks know who you are if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like say if you&#x27;re posting illegal shit online.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not perfect, but requiring a purchase to post introduces some safety mechanism against people posting gnarly stuff--moreso than just emails and ip addresses.
And if you don&#x27;t want to post, you don&#x27;t have to buy anything.
And if you do want to post, but you don&#x27;t want to buy anything, you can use open platforms with their own gatekeeping like Bluesky.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;aren-t-the-banks-just-as-bad&quot;&gt;Aren&#x27;t the banks just as bad?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe.
But one problem at a time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-15&quot;&gt;Continue to part 15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;12&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, things that are so heinous, that even if they aren&#x27;t illegal in the uploader&#x27;s juristiction it will result in excommunication.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 15 - You&#x27;re invited</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-15/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-15/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-15/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-open-invitation-to-the-advancement&quot;&gt;An open invitation to The Advancement&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been working on solving the problem of advertising and digital identity for close to a decade.
I&#x27;ve released things in fits and starts just trying to get people on board with the idea of not putting their birthdays into random online forms.
But the road to progress is always winding.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on January 20th, four smiling billionaires, two nazi salutes, and the subsequent fellating of these dickheads by &quot;entrepreneurs,&quot; and wallstreet bros, gave a very simple entry point into doing something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t a political thing, and it isn&#x27;t an American thing.
Regardless of who you are, wanting a world where your every online action isn&#x27;t spied upon shouldn&#x27;t be controversial.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#x27;s focus on that for like a year.
We&#x27;ll be back to fighting about politics soon enough, but before that let&#x27;s take these billionaires down a peg.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call the group who does this, The Advancemet, and everyone, except for actual nazis, are invited.
All you have to do is install a browser extension, and&#x2F;or download an app.
Those of us in The Advancement who make those things, will take it from there.
And you can spend your time doing whatever you love to do, and not have to worry about billionaires in your bedroom.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-want-to-get-involved&quot;&gt;I want to get involved&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever started a movement?
Neither have I, but I have joined some clubs, so let&#x27;s start there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s how you join a club, it&#x27;s nice because it works the same as the bar: you show up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then to get involved...well I&#x27;ll let Captain Ron explain how it works.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=tr82gPYI24I&amp;amp;t=180s&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;img.youtube.com&#x2F;vi&#x2F;tr82gPYI24I&#x2F;0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Captain Ron gives a new sailor an incentive&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just start doing stuff.
It doesn&#x27;t matter if its small, or special, or crucial, or anything.
Just start doing stuff with the club, because the point isn&#x27;t that one thing, the point for the club, in Ron&#x27;s case here the crew, is to get the boat all the way to where it&#x27;s going, and that&#x27;s a long-term goal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-on-the-boat&quot;&gt;Getting on the boat&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, anthropologists were still saying we didn&#x27;t know how humans got all the way to remote islands like Hawaii, and Easter Island.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I knew.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone built a boat.
And then that person said, &quot;I&#x27;m heading that way, who&#x27;s coming with me?&quot;
And somehow enough people joined that person on their boat that when they got to Hawaii they didn&#x27;t die immediately.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Centuries after these explorers ventured forth, I sat at a bar with my friend where someone posited that we would never go to Mars because who would risk that flight.
I said ridiculous!
Why?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we should never understimate humanity&#x27;s desire to get on the boat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past decade I&#x27;ve been building a boat.
It floats, but it still needs some work.
But the volcano in the middle of the island is rumbling, and threatening to pour nazis down its sides, and so we&#x27;ve got to get on the water soon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m going to keep building the boat one way or another.
If you want to help, you just have to come aboard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to do that until the end of February or so, is going to be to join us on discord: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;discord.gg&#x2F;M5V8Xwm&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;discord.gg&#x2F;M5V8Xwm&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or email me at zach at planetnine.app -- that one still works for now &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There&#x27;s room for everyone in the revolution friend.
I hope to see you aboard.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 2 - The twentieth century</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-2/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-2/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-2/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;interoperability&quot;&gt;Interoperability&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For historical reasons, phone numbers and email have a very useful property: interoperability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interoperability is an idea in electronic systems, which has largely been forgotten in our modern technical world, which is dominated by gigantic corporations looking to extract every nickel from your every digital move.
The story of how we got there is worthy of a read, but I&#x27;ll try and give the quick hits here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexander Graham Bell invents the telephone in the late nineteenth century, and in true American fashion immediately establishes one of the most ruthless monopolistic corporations to ever exist: American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&amp;amp;T).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1913, AT&amp;amp;T bought the other telecommunications monopoly Western Union, who had consolidated the telegraph system as the telephone took market share.
This was a little too close in time to Teddy Roosevelt&#x27;s trust bustin&#x27; movement, and brought about the ire of the US government.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with commupance from the federal government, AT&amp;amp;T negotiated an out of court settlement called the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Kingsbury_Commitment&quot;&gt;Kingsbury Commitment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
The Kingsbury Commitment forced AT&amp;amp;T to divest itself from Western Union, and, important to our phone number story, forced them to allow smaller networks to connect to their long-distance infrastructure.
This required AT&amp;amp;T and the other networks to start down the path on standardizing some sort of protocol for keeping their identifiers unique, and interoperable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus the phone number was born.
Of course phone numbers existed before then, and the history of how they worked before these networks got so large that everything was automated is actually pretty interesting (see for instance &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Julia_O&amp;#x27;Connor&quot;&gt;Julia O&#x27;connor&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Strowger_switch&quot;&gt;Strowger switch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), but for our story here there are two things of note.
First, this was the first time that a unified numerical identifier was granted to people by a non-government entity, and two to make up for AT&amp;amp;T having to share its network, the Kingsbury Commitment made it so that AT&amp;amp;T could boot unauthorized connections to its network.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;banana-phone&quot;&gt;Banana phone&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&#x2F;.&#x2F;carterphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A carterphone was a device that would connect to a telephone network via radio so people could walkey talkey other people over the phone&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Carterfone was a work of art&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sixties, Thomas Carter invented the Carterfone, a device which was essentially a walkey-talkey connected to a phone receiver so folks could talk via radio to other folks on a phone.
AT&amp;amp;T magnanimously told Carter to pound sand when he tried to use their network.
Carter, whose invention was made for oil field workers so they could call for help when away from phone lines, took the issue to the FCC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time Carter&#x27;s case reached the FCC, the agency had started to recognize the need for computers to connect to each other.
They used the carterfone case as an opportunity to revisit AT&amp;amp;T&#x27;s ability to block devices from connecting to their network.
AT&amp;amp;T was faced with a similar reality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that connecting computers might just be lucrative enough to warrant competition against AT&amp;amp;T&#x27;s network, AT&amp;amp;T and the FCC use the case as an opportunity to open AT&amp;amp;Ts network, for a modest fee of course, to the rapidly growing networks of computers popping up around the country.
The Law of Unintended Consquences being what it is, Carter&#x27;s case led to two decades of AT&amp;amp;T dominance, and then it&#x27;s breakup in the early 80s.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to track down a picture of Thomas Carter to see what this legend looked like.
I was not disappointed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&#x2F;.&#x2F;tom-carter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thomas Carter looks like a character out of Dynasty with a ten gallon hat, bolo tie, mutton chops, and amber aviators&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&#x27;t get much more American than some guy jury-rigging a way for those in the oil fields of Texas to phone home to let their people know they haven&#x27;t blown up yet that day taking on the largest company in the country, and winning so that it can ultimately make more money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;multi-user&quot;&gt;Multi-user&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These newfangled computers that were using AT&amp;amp;T&#x27;s network to talk to each other had a problem though.
Unlike humans that have distinct voices, the machines all talked the same.
So to have any reasonable notion of who was behind the machine, we had to introduce &lt;em&gt;auth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays there are a lot of auth protocols, but back in those days it was good ol&#x27; username and password.
You need both because passwords can&#x27;t be unique, and usernames don&#x27;t need to be secret.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This auth-tuple can&#x27;t be shared between things that need to be logged into since those two things can&#x27;t trust each other.
This means different online things can&#x27;t just assume that you username in one system is the same as the same username in another system.
And thus, almost by definition, being user on a computer at the time meant giving up on interoperability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;america-goes-online&quot;&gt;America goes online&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s an interesting problem in statistics called the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Birthday_problem&quot;&gt;birthday problem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
It shows that you only need 23 people chosen at random to have a greater than 50% chance of two of them having the same birthday.
The reason for this comes down to some simple math.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probabilities are usually represented as fractions less than one.
In this case, if we had only two people the probability that they would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; have the same birthday is 364&#x2F;365 since there are 364 days the second person could be born on that would be different than the first person&#x27;s birthday.
The third person would then have a probability of 363&#x2F;365 instead because now there are two different days that people have birthdays on.
You continue ticking down the numerator for each person added to the test.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&#x2F;.&#x2F;birthday.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A colorful picture to try and hide the boring math behind this problem&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find the total probability of this series of probabilities, you just multiply them all together, and when you do that for 23 people you get the probability that two people will have the same birthday just over 50%.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with the price of beans in Boston?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well that whole username and password thing was working just fine for computers connecting to things, but as the number of people grew, people started birthday probleming their desired usernames.
There are somewhere around 20,000 common six-letter words in English.
You know how many people need to be selecting words before there&#x27;s a 50% chance of two people selecting the same one?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;167&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of you who are known as ponies724 know what I&#x27;m talking about.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn&#x27;t so bad when there was just one thing to sign into, but as places with usernames proliferated you had to deal with someone snaking you on ponies724.
Then you&#x27;d have to &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; not only your password, but which incarnation of your username to use.
Zweibel is German of onion, but it&#x27;s also two-bell.
So when it&#x27;s taken I use Dreibel (three-bell).
There&#x27;s even one place where I&#x27;m Vierbel (four-bell).
I don&#x27;t remember where that place is, but I remember it&#x27;s out there somewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the online folks went searching for a &quot;username&quot; that was unique to the user so they could carry them around with them.
Something cheap, and easy to give to anyone.
Maybe something where ponies724 could just be ponies alongside other ponies.
Something like email.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-ve-got-mail&quot;&gt;You&#x27;ve got mail&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen, I was there.
Hearing the digitized low-fi voice of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Elwood_Edwards&quot;&gt;Elwood Edwards&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; was awesome, and the first few emails you got were so novel and cool.
But soon there would be such a deluge of emails that had to be forwarded to ten friends to avert disaster, that it was impossible to keep up.
Obviously those were all spam since nothing bad has happened since the mid 90s...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email was then, and mostly still is now, the simplest open and interoperable thing that exists in cyberspace.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-2&#x2F;.&#x2F;walter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Walter from the Big Lebowsky saying &amp;quot;I can get you a toe by 3pm,&amp;quot; but toe is crossed out and says &amp;quot;email server&amp;quot; instead&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All you need is a domain and a computer, and you can set up an email server.
Now if you lookup how to do this you&#x27;ll find a lot of things telling you not to, and the reason for that is that nowadays there&#x27;re a ton of hoops to jump through to make it so that your emails actually go through.
But I can&#x27;t really tell if that&#x27;s to keep the spam out, or to keep the people beholden to the email giants who are gatekeeping this in the first place.
I mean, how do you feel they&#x27;re doing at keeping out spam?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;email-and-or-phone-number&quot;&gt;Email and&#x2F;or phone number&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email served &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; like the phone number for users.
It became a single identifier that people could use everywhere, but the systems it was being used with weren&#x27;t connected together--or at least weren&#x27;t connected in a way that would benefit users.
But we need to get to the next millenium to start filling in that story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the internet got going in full swing, AOL started to lose its shine, and people started looking to alternatives for email.
Hotmail, and Yahoo were the major players of the late nineties, and a lot of people jumped over.
There were other factors of course, but the incredible flood of users claiming free emails is partly what fueled the dotcom bubble that saw Yahoo with a market valuation of $125 billion, and made Microsoft the highest market valued company in the world (do you see a trend here?).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in 2000 the bubble would pop, and as so often happens the human phoenix of innovation would rise from the ashes.
And as so doubly often happens, that phoenix would exploit the masses for profit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-3&quot;&gt;Continue on to part 3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;auth is short for authentication (authn) and authorization (authz). The former establishes who you are, and the latter establishes that you are able to do what you&#x27;re trying to do. I like writing about auth, which is why I&#x27;m going to leave this as a footnote, and not add fifty paragraphs to this post.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Elwood was paid not one, but two cool Benjamins for his recording of perhaps the most well-known voice acting of the 90s.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 3 - Out of the ashes</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-3/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-3/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-3/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;ahoy-matey&quot;&gt;Ahoy matey&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the business world of the dotcom boom was preparing to burst, consumers were starting to learn that while waiting for an image to load on the internet was still slow, once it was on your machine, things were fast.
Users started branching out into other media like music, and certainly not pornographic videos.
The likes of Napster, Limewire, Kazaa, and people just torrenting things left and right, was a One Piece-level deployment of piracy unseen before on Earth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And suddenly firstname.lastname@companywhohasmycreditcard.com wasn&#x27;t such a great identifier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;don-t-be-evil&quot;&gt;Don&#x27;t be evil&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s so hard some times to remember that the world may have once been any way other than it is now.
In the early aughts the internet wasn&#x27;t the ad-infested garbage pile it is now.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the mid-nineties if you wanted to share a website with someone, you wrote down its url on a piece of paper, and handed it to them in class.
I remember vividly reading and copying the urlencoded equivalent of antidisestablishmentarianism into netscape&#x27;s url bar, and hoping it didn&#x27;t land me somewhere weird.
To ammeliorate this pain for web denizens, various solutions arrived.
One of these, was the humble search engine, and the best ones around were Yahoo, Google, AltaVista, and Ask Jeeves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thing is, Google was still private at the time, while the others were all public.
So when the dotcom bubble burst and imploded the other three&#x27;s valuations, Google was comparitively unscathed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gudstory.s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com&#x2F;wp-content&#x2F;uploads&#x2F;2022&#x2F;07&#x2F;22030823&#x2F;Dot-Com-Bubble-burst-750x586.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The dotcom bubble bursting disappeared over 1.5 trillion dollars from the stock market&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Google was still private for the same reason the bubble burst: lots of users, but no way to monetize them.
All those companies that had just evaporated from the bubble bursting had the silly notion that people would &quot;pay&quot; for the services they provided.
Google wasn&#x27;t the first of course, but they were certainly the ones who went HAM on the idea of monetizing user behavior through advertising.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They started by putting ads on their search results page, but in 2003 they released the real money maker.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#13&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
Google&#x27;s ad sense platform would let content creators drop some small snippets of code on their sites that would serve ads to users based on what the users search history.
Serving &lt;em&gt;relevant&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; ads to users improved engagement, which was more profitable for Google, the company advertising, and the content creator...well at least at first.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the money faucet was turned on, Google&#x27;s thirst for information became insatiable.
Their motto, &quot;Don&#x27;t be evil&quot; let everyone know just how innocuous their data collection was.
Their plan was to release free services for the benefit of humanity, and for their troubles they&#x27;d just collect some data here and there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2004, less than twelve months after releasing ad sense, they released the ultimate money making service: gmail.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2004, Yahoo, and Hotmail emails were decidedly uncool.
And forget about it if you were still using aol.
In fact most tech was pretty uncool since it put a bunch of people out of work just a few years before.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one cool thing though.
In 2001 the soon to be largest company in the world had figured out a device for people to put all that pirated music on, and somehow convinced the world that if your headphones weren&#x27;t white, you weren&#x27;t even really listening to music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the iPod was cool in large part because it was exclusive, and it was exclusive the old-fashioned way--Apple made it prohibitively expensive.
Exclusivity in tech was a novel concept from the dotcom days of everyone and their brother being able to sign up for everything.
So when Google launched gmail as a &quot;beta&quot; that people had to be invited to, it created exclusivity, and suddenly the decades old tech of email, long rendered useless by spam and garbage, was somehow cool enough again for everyone to switch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today about a quarter of all humans have a gmail account.
I&#x27;ll leave it to you how they&#x27;re living up to their motto.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So great, Google corners the market on one of the universally held identifiers out there.
The other, of course, is your phone number.
Seems fitting your next move would be to acquire a phone company right?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2005 Google acquired Android to do just that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-4&quot;&gt;Continue to part 4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make your money from ads, I&#x27;ve got no beef with you. The ad-dispensing companies have made it their mission to encroach on your creative space as much as possible to extract value from your hard work. I&#x27;m here to help carve out a path to you making more money in addition to how you use the ad networks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;13&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at Google&#x27;s P&amp;amp;L statements, you&#x27;ll see that search comprises by far the largest part of their revenue. What I mean here by saying the &quot;real money maker&quot; is that the adsense platform is what put google into every nook and cranny of your internet, and allowed them to charge what they charge for knowing who you are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Google created a parent company Alphabet, Alphabet dropped the don&#x27;t be evil. The don&#x27;t be evil line moved to Google&#x27;s code of conduct. I wanted to avoid inferring anything from this, but when you change something like don&#x27;t be evil to anything else, it&#x27;s worth a questioning glance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 4 - Looking for my space</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-4/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-4/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-4/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;humans-are-social-animals-right&quot;&gt;Humans are social animals right?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the early aughts, my friend bought the domain mauledbytigers.com and set up a message board.
The only significant world event I can remember circulating on the board was the Mr. Hands video, an event that if you do not know about I highly suggest you do not look up.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
That event happened in 2005, so that gives you the year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was known as Lazer back in those days, and part of the Chicago music scene.
It was a big scene, and my contribution largely insignificant, but I did meet a lot of people, and there are more than a few who know me as Lazer to this day.
The problem, of course, was how to keep up with all of these friends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily tech had the answer again!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2002, an enterprising Canadian named Jonathan Abrams started work on a new social network.
In early 2003 he launched Friendster.
Friendster introduced a new problem to the internet--hyper scaling.
AOL had topped off around three million users.
A decade later, Friendster would hit 100 million users, and making things work for those many people was a bit of a challenge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-thumb-on-the-scale&quot;&gt;A thumb on the scale&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendster was the first, but the two that came next, at least in the states, were the real players to define the social networking era.
One lives on in my mind as a symbol of freedom and awesomeness, and the other is possibly the most damaging entity on the planet.
Let&#x27;s start with the former.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-4&#x2F;.&#x2F;tom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The legendary picture of Tom from MySpace&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re over a certain age, this image needs no introduction.
When you signed up for MySpace, this was your first friend: Tom from MySpace.
As I write this, tech billionaires are capitulating to right-wing hostility, and endeavoring to make life as hard as possible for everyone other than themselves.
So the fact that Tom sold MySpace for $500 million+, and then just kind of disappeared, is really refreshing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Friendster, and MySpace, the Winklevoss Twins had the genius idea of ripping off those websites, but making it exclusive to Harvard students so as to separate themselves from the dirty plebes around them.
They turned to the obviously talented programmer of the website they used to drunkenly rate coeds on campus, and together that braintrust created Facebook.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has been written on these first hyperscaled social networks, and why Facebook won when the others didn&#x27;t.
Like with anything else with pontificating pundits, most of it is reductive, and kind of lame.
Let me give you the inside scoop.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MySpace had this amazing feature where you could grab snippets of web code, and paste it onto your home page.
If you wanted your page to be bubblegum pink with sparkles around the text, and rainbows raining down, all you had to do was paste in some text.
And that&#x27;s how it should be, because, after all, &lt;em&gt;it was your fucking space.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a performance standpoint, this made everything load slow as molasses, and for anyone who hadn&#x27;t been online ten years ago, made the site pretty unusable.
Us twenty-somethings were the target demographic, and we loved it, but it left the younger folk kind of uninterested (not that big of a deal).
For the older folk though it left Facebook with the perfect opportunity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody at Facebook had the critical insight that for most people, and definitely anyone who has left the devil may care time of their lives, their friends just weren&#x27;t all that interesting.
Instead, using their friends to target shared interests in a timeline feed kept people more engaged.
And the timeline feed loaded fast, and always had good stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of digital monetization there&#x27;s a big difference between people in their mid-twenties, and people over thirty-five because the latter has money, and the former doesn&#x27;t.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a brief moment in time, everyone was touching code just a bit to make things fun on the internet.
It was beautiful, and important, and that shard of collective creativity was shattered by the most boring gray with blue accents bs like the time thieves in Momo.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-4&#x2F;.&#x2F;totally-rad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A meticulously curated black and pink themed MySpace page&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-4&#x2F;.&#x2F;utter-garbage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;facebook&amp;#39;s garbage gray boring interface with some total chaches in a profile pic&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It could have been this, but instead we got ads&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The people who like this UI are the ones you worry about &quot;making new friends&quot; online now&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, now we know who came out on top--a company who has single-handedly advanced disinformation and destructive rabbit holes in the name of ad-based profit moreso than any entity in history.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom, I wish you the best, but I wish you&#x27;d never left.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-5&quot;&gt;Continue to part 5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told you not to look it up&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story is a little different than what I&#x27;ve represented here, and this is mostly based on my recollection of the film the Social Network, which was itself inaccurate, but I don&#x27;t much care. Facebook is the largest deseminator of disinformation on the planet, and I&#x27;m not too worried about them getting a taste of their own medicine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 5 - Aristophanes was right</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-5/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-5/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-5/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;oauth-and-web-2-0&quot;&gt;OAuth, and Web 2.0&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006 a relatively minor player in this narrative joined the party.
Twitter quickly made waves because it was, by the standards of the time, open.
If you were cool, people with twitter could tweet right from your site.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually Twitter&#x27;s openness ran into the problem that every open thing does, which is that bandits show up to shut down the party.
In this case, the trouble was that people entering their Twitter password into random websites wasn&#x27;t the best security practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save the people from themselves, some very smart computer folk got together and came up with a protocol called OAuth.
It&#x27;s successor OAuth2.0 would become as close to singularly dominant as software gets, being the method used by Google, Meta, Microsoft, and thus anything that uses them for authentication.
The original &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rfc-editor.org&#x2F;rfc&#x2F;rfc5849&quot;&gt;OAuth rfc&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a pithy 38 pages, and well worth the read if you want to know more about auth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is oauth?
Well basically it says that you cannot be trusted to sign into things, so instead you&#x27;ll just sign in to things you trust like Google and&#x2F;or Meta, and they&#x27;ll handle, out of the goodness of their hearts, the hard part of keeping you safe from the internet bandits.
For their troubles, they&#x27;ll get an ongoing list of every service you use from now until the end of time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds like an even trade right?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-smart-phone&quot;&gt;The smart phone&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January of 2007, Steve Jobs stepped onto the Apple stage in his trademark black turtleneck, and told the world that Apple had put an iPod in a phone with the internet.
Missing the opportunity to call it the phoneputer, the iPhone would launch that summer starting the smart phone on the trajectory towards arguably the most important product category on Earth.
The first android devices would launch the next year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-5&#x2F;.&#x2F;steve.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steve Jobs unveils the iPhone&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2005, only about 10-15% of humans owned computers, and none of those who did could take them &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and use them &lt;em&gt;all the gosh darn time.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
Fifteen years later, half of all humans owned computers, with almost all of that half owning a tiny computer that was coming with them everywhere they go.
And pretty much all of them were signed in to Google and Facebook.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cloud&quot;&gt;The cloud&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2007 was an auspicious year for humanity&#x27;s story with computers.
A plucky book selling company named Amazon had grown to a large enough size that they were having trouble keeping everyone&#x27;s carts up to date.
To address this, they built a system called Dynamo (now branded as DynamoDB), and presented it to the world in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.allthingsdistributed.com&#x2F;files&#x2F;amazon-dynamo-sosp2007.pdf&quot;&gt;a paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at an ACM conference in the fall.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a watershed moment in distributed systems design because it allowed for the system to run on a large number of (relatively) cheap machines, as opposed to the hugely expensive enterprise systems available at the time.
People started wondering if they could lease time on these servers, and AWS was born.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second iPhone, and the nascent android phones came with app stores.
This significantly lowered the barrier of entry for developers to reach users, while also providing a rapidly growing userbase eager to use their crispy new devices.
Speed was the name of the game, and if app creators could offload the boring backend stuff to someone as prestegious as Amazon, what was a few bucks a month?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This setup for backend stuff was collectively called the Cloud, and if you were around in 06 and 07 you heard it ad nauseum, but no one could explain what the heck the Cloud was.
So allow me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cloud meant that instead of buying and owning the computer(s) your software ran on, you could rent computers from someone else.
Whether that was good or bad at the time I think could be discussed, but it certainly doesn&#x27;t seem great now that two of the three largest cloud platforms are run by the world&#x27;s largest advertiser, and the eCommerce shop that sells you all the garbage you get advertised to about.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was nearly twenty years ago.
Moore&#x27;s Law suggests that machines are 1,000 times more powerful today.
Wright&#x27;s Law suggests that that should correlate to a 90% decrease in price.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-5&#x2F;.&#x2F;aws.png&quot; alt=&quot;The substantial growth of Amazon&amp;#39;s web service&amp;#39;s revenue growth&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you feel like things in the cloud are 90% cheaper?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-6&quot;&gt;Continue to part 6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part - It sure does rhyme</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-6/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-6/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-6/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;hey-where-d-my-money-go&quot;&gt;Hey where&#x27;d my money go?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2008, no...let&#x27;s go back a bit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks hold your money, and rather than charging you for the privelage of holding it, they re-invest it and make money off of that.
Now if they invest in something nice and safe like a mortgage that someone can afford, your money&#x27;s safe, and the bank makes its income.
But if the bank goes and lays your money on red, and it spins black, your money&#x27;s gone.
That might not be a huge deal if the bank can make that money back before you ask for it, but if it doesn&#x27;t that&#x27;s a problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1920s, the bankers invested heavily in a stock market that could seemingly do no wrong.
Then in 1929 it all came crashing down, and plunged the country into the Great Depression.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For their role in causing the trouble, the banks were &quot;broken up&quot; with an act of congress known as Glass-Steagall.
Glass-Steagall said, &quot;you can take people&#x27;s money, or you can invest in risky bullshit, but you can&#x27;t do both.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things went pretty well with respect to banks not causing global financial collapse for the rest of the twentieth century, but all good things come to an end.
In 1999 pretty much everyone in DC was ready to let the banks go back to the roulette table, and Glass-Steagall was repealed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the thing about money is that a sudden increase in its supply doesn&#x27;t make more things to purchase appear out of thin air.
Instead the increased demand causes the price of the existing assets to rise.
If they rise fast enough, this is called a bubble.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the dotcom bubble that happened in, &lt;em&gt;checks notes&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, 2001.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-6&#x2F;.&#x2F;gs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A timeline of market crashes with the timeline of Glass-Steagall super imposed showing correlation between its repeal and the constant financial crashes of the 2000s&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well correlation may not equal causation, but like maybe that shouldn&#x27;t matter when we&#x27;re dealing with banks playing with our money&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily everyone learned their lesson from that bubble burst, and decided to invest in the much safer realm of real estate mortgages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same increased demand that caused the dotcom bubble, had a different effect in real estate where the price of the investment vehicles was much less volatile.
In order to meet the increased demand, lenders had to create more investment vehicles.
Part of this was done by creating convoluted derivatives of derivatives of investments, and part of this was done just by giving people more mortgages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you combine these two things you end up with assets that are both risky, and impossible to assess the risk of.
In September of 2008, a large investment bank, Lehman Brothers, filed for bankruptcy.
When they did it &quot;broke the buck,&quot; a term used when a money market fund&#x27;s net asset value falls below $1 per share.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#8&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All hell broke loose, and if you were around back then, it felt like the sky was falling.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;like-a-p5x-we-rise&quot;&gt;Like a p5x we rise&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the nice thing about the whole housing crisis thing is that it only really hurt the folks who shouldn&#x27;t have been getting mortgages in the first place, the hard working people dependent on those people, the communities those people lived in, and was in no way bias along racial lines (this is of course not nice at all, but not being snarky makes it too depressing).
The people and banks with plenty of money were largely fine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because when you give someone a mortgage you actually own the property the mortgage is for.
So when they can&#x27;t pay, you foreclose on them, and now you own the house.
Sure you take a little hit on the house&#x27;s value, but you&#x27;re a bank so you know that value&#x27;s going to come back up.
After all, there&#x27;re a bunch of people who need housing now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now everyone needed a new thing to invest in.
Enter Andreessen Horowitz aka a16z, and the VCs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked ClaudeAI what the difference between the VCs, and the dotcom investors are, and it gave me some nonsense about how companies are more proven these days, and blah blah blah.
It&#x27;s the same song and dance: too much money chasing too little value.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in life you&#x27;ve just got to hang in there.
Friendster and MySpace went home too early, leaving Facebook hanging around the DJ Booth when the after hours crowd poured in.
The phoneputers became the perfect device for all those folks without houses, and since people get bored they were hungry for something to do on the machines.
All the doom scrollers needed to scale was piles of money, and since nothing else was appetizing at the time, the VC-era took off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-7&quot;&gt;Continue to part 7&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So banks don&#x27;t hold a lot of cash, because cash is better used in investments. So to handle their day-to-day operation they borrow money for really short terms (like for a day) from money market funds. They pay this back with a small amount of interest, and that gets paid to the investors in the money market. When Lehman Brothers collapsed, the debt it owed to the money market represented money that was effectively gone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 7 - At least you have the same rights as money</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-7/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-7/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-7/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-if-we-just-got-rid-of-money&quot;&gt;What if we just got rid of money?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little more than a month after Lehman Brothers broke the buck, Satoshi Nakamoto, who may or may not exist, published a whitepaper entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bitcoin.org&#x2F;bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;&quot;Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
In it he described a system that used asymmetric cryptography, and a new kind of datastore called a blockchain to allow for a transaction system.
In the system, transaction values would be represented by a fungible token called a bitcoin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are you&#x27;ve heard of this system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin, and the crypto category isn&#x27;t really a part of this story.
I introduce it here because Satoshi introduced a third identifier for people: the public key, and also because it&#x27;s the asset class that joins what&#x27;s in the next few paragraphs in being the money sink that the banks need to not crash everything again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-bubble&quot;&gt;More bubble?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you may be wondering what, if anything, happened to make it so that the bubbles of 2001 and 2008 didn&#x27;t continue to happen throughout the 2010&#x27;s.
Well, it turns out there was a crucial asset class that had long gone ignored in the hyper-capitalist United States.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2010, the US Supreme Court passed the Citizens United decision, which decided that the first amendment considered money to be speech, and that there could be no limit on political contributions from institutions.
And you know... politics have been totally cool in the US ever since.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-7&#x2F;.&#x2F;money.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A huge pile of cash announces its 2016, so as to rule over its fellow citizens&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever you stand politically, I hope you can at least recognize the disparity between the US, and other countries&#x27; approaches to online protections.
A reality that certainly isn&#x27;t helped by US companies being able to pour unlimited cash into political campaigns.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU&#x27;s General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) is the most notable.
It&#x27;s what&#x27;s responsible for those giant cookie banners that show up everywhere on the web.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the GDPR, everyone would get to track you without you being none the wiser--just like the gigantocorps would like.
But the GDPR&#x27;s reach across the pond is limited, and with politics being the cash-hungry beast it is, the gigantocorps coffers wield non-negligible influence around here, and would regardless of who&#x27;s in charge.
We&#x27;ll have to wait about a decade for where this really reers its head, but if you&#x27;re already feeling uneasy, I wouldn&#x27;t blame you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-8&quot;&gt;Continue to part 8&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 8 - The cell saga</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-8/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-8/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-8/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-factorin&quot;&gt;Two-factorin&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#x27;s the late aughts, you&#x27;re Google, you have a near monopoly on where people are logging in because they&#x27;re all using your email, and now, thanks to the benevolence of your Android operating system, you know everyone&#x27;s phone numbers, and can even construct a social graph similar to Facebook&#x27;s via access to people&#x27;s contacts.
There&#x27;s just one rub: that darn iPhone&#x27;s around, and Apple doesn&#x27;t want to share.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the braintrust came up with the genius idea of making you&#x27;re already secure accounts &lt;em&gt;even more secure&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by adding two-factor authentication via sms.
Google released this 2FA in 2011 because the world was clearly unable to function without it up until that point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rise of two-factor authentication via sms provides an important lesson on how additional complexity often leads to &lt;em&gt;less&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; security, and not more.
Whenever you deal with consumers who might be miffed if you lose all their data, you need to provide a way for them to recover accounts.
Most of the time you do that via email.
But what do you do if the account they care about is email?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google, and others with 2FA, said, &quot;no problem, we&#x27;ll just use your phone number.&quot;
But then the question became what if you had your phone stolen, or you lost it.
Well then the security of 2FA would be dependent on the carriers&#x27; ability to protect your interests.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-8&#x2F;.&#x2F;bandit.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A sim swap image, with a bandit dressed like the bandit he is&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;If only all bandits would show up in uniform&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&#x27;ve worked retail, and I have the utmost respect for people who do, and their capabilities.
I do not have much faith in the corporations who pay these good people a pittance to be on their frontline.
A company who does that, probably isn&#x27;t going to put much thought into making sure you&#x27;re you when you go to replace your phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vulnerability here wasn&#x27;t exposed for a while because, despite how you might feel, the Harry Potter fanfic in your google drive isn&#x27;t all that valuable.
But when crypto became valuable enough for bandits to want to steal, they started stealing people&#x27;s phone numbers by just going into stores and requesting sim cards as that person in what&#x27;s called a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;SIM_swap_scam&quot;&gt;SIM swap attack&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-you-at&quot;&gt;Where you at?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you might be wondering what&#x27;s the big deal with phone numbers in the first place.
If you&#x27;re old like me you might remember a time when we just published all our phone numbers in a book, with our name and addresses, and then gave everyone that book for free.
If you&#x27;re not old like me I&#x27;d be curious what your thoughts are on that practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what the cell in cellular refers to?
I hadn&#x27;t until I started researching this whole rigamarole.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.researchgate.net&#x2F;profile&#x2F;Jianjun-Yang-3&#x2F;publication&#x2F;263316201&#x2F;figure&#x2F;fig2&#x2F;AS:667618981715968@1536184177139&#x2F;A-topology-of-a-cellular-network.png&quot; alt=&quot;A simple sketch of the cells in a cellular network&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A cellular network&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our phones communicate wirelessly, and since they&#x27;re small, the distance that they can communicate at is fairly limited.
So to accommodate them, cell towers are setup every so often around the Earth for them to connect to.
These towers define a cell, and as you travel the Earth your phone switches from tower to tower as you move from cell to cell.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the telecomms companies aren&#x27;t supposed to provide this data to anyone, but &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.vice.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;article&#x2F;fcc-propose-fines-verizon-att-sprint-tmobile-selling-location-data&#x2F;&quot;&gt;of course they do&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, because when they got caught the FCC fined them a whole $200 million, a little under one dollar for everyone whose location they were selling.
But even if the telecomms didn&#x27;t sell this data, your phone would report it back anyways through background networking tasks, or just plain old checking your phone at a red light.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now location wouldn&#x27;t be that big of a deal I guess if you didn&#x27;t have at your disposal the largest database of location-based info on Earth.
But of course the company doing all of this &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the company with the largest database of location-based info on Earth. Almost as if this whole getcha phone to getcha location was planned or something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what do you do with all this info?
Well you know that creepy thing that happens sometimes where you were talking about a thing with a friend and then you start getting ads for it?
Well I have no doubt that sometimes you&#x27;re being listened to, but most of the time what&#x27;s happening is that one of you googles that thing, and then because google (and the rest of the gigantocorps for that matter) know that you were with that person, the ad netwroks serve you an ad about that thing too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-9&quot;&gt;Continue to part 9&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Part 9 - Are you entertained?</title>
        <published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-9/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-9/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/you_are_not_a_number/part-9/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-boob-tube&quot;&gt;The boob tube&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The television was invented in the 1920s.
Its history is long, and interesting, but out of scope for this doc.
Except for one part.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1941, before a sunny baseball game between the Brooklyn Dodgers, and the Philadelphia Phillies, a brief ad, the first television ad in the US aired.
It cost $9 (close to $200 today) and aired to about 4,000 people.
I have no doubt that this would have opened the flood gates regardless of what was going on in the world, but as it would happen 1941 was a rather auspicious year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 7th of 1941, the Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor and the United States became a full participant in World War II.
To produce the kind of war-time provisions needed to fight that war, the government rationed a bunch of things.
Pretty much any large manufacturer was rationed, or flat out bought up, by the government.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For their troubles, the government set up the War Advertising Council.
The council&#x27;s mandate was to provide free or cheap advertising for these harmed businesses while also supporting the war effort.
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nationalgeographic.com&#x2F;history&#x2F;article&#x2F;141207-world-war-advertising-consumption-anniversary-people-photography-culture&quot;&gt;You can see some of the sweet ads here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-9&#x2F;.&#x2F;wac.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A war advertising council coca-cola ad of a sailor and a woman sharing a coke&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WAC, an auspicious acronym given their mandate, was essentially the propaganda engine for the war effort, but because it was American, it made sure to sell tires alongside white picket fences, and obedient dames for when you got home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the war ended, the US stood as pretty much the only industrial power not bombed significantly, and a bunch of twenty-somethings came home with cash in their pockets.
The WAC disbanded, companies started producing again, and all they had to do was replace uniforms with suits, and they had their advertising ready to go.
Print, film, and radio were all known mediums, but one of the things all those soldiers were buying were tvs--the perfect new medium for companies looking to reach an audience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&#x27;t take long before one of the largest marketing firms in the country ACNielsen realized that advertisers would benefit from, and thus pay them for information about who was watching what.
To do this they went to a couple of towns in America, and had the good people there write down what shows they were watching.
And this is how tv ratings worked for almost four decades, until cable joined the party.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With cable, Nielsen was able to make a box.
You could attach this box in between your cable and your tv, and it would record what you were watching for Nielsen.
For your troubles, Nielsen would pay you a couple bucks, and sell your demographic data and viewing habits for a bit more than those couple of bucks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-searchlights&quot;&gt;The searchlights&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was maybe twelve years old when the family was driving home from some dinner at some American suburban culinary stalwart, when we saw the hollywood spotlights scanning the skies near our house.
Intrigued, we ventured over to the grand opening of the hottest chain sweeping the nation in the first half of the nineties: Blockbuster Video.
We of course had a perfectly fine video rental shop we already frequented, but Blockbuster was new and shiny, and closer to home, so we were hooked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-9&#x2F;.&#x2F;blockbuster.png&quot; alt=&quot;The glorious blastic blockbuster video casette cases&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you don&#x27;t know the joy of cracking one of these open, and heteronormative act of inserting that casette into the VCR...idk maybe that&#x27;s why the kids are having less sex these days&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockbuster had a novel instrument for us--the Blockbuster card.
At our local rental shop, you&#x27;d just leave your name, and they&#x27;d put you into their ancient phosphorescent green machine, and you&#x27;d be on your way.
Blockbuster had UPCs and scanners, and a laminated wallet-stuffer you could use to show people you were cool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to Blockbuster, there were some retailers which collected customer data into a nationwide database, but nothing that came close to Blockbuster&#x27;s reach.
At its peak, Blockbuster had close to a fifth of the US as members, all just givin&#x27; away when they rented War of the Roses four weekends in a row to get through a breakup.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Blockbuster would blunder the world&#x27;s transition from physicial to digital media, and Netflix would pick up the ball.
What Blockbuster was doing with your rental habits seems lost to the ages, but Netflix has partnered with Nielsen to provide that information at the very least.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there you go, your tv too, just spying on you for advertisers to sell you more stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;you_are_not_a_number&#x2F;part-10&quot;&gt;Continue to part 10&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Writing a Matrix Digital Rain</title>
        <published>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/matrix-digital-rain/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/matrix-digital-rain/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/matrix-digital-rain/">&lt;p&gt;Author: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;wick3dr0se&quot;&gt;wick3dr0se&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;writing-a-matrix-digital-rain&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#writing-a-matrix-digital-rain&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: writing-a-matrix-digital-rain&quot;&gt;Writing a Matrix Digital Rain&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;matrix-digital-rain&#x2F;matrix.gif&quot; alt=&quot;matrix digital rain gif&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a terminal based matrix digital rain is fairly simple; Even utilizing raw ANSI escape sequences, we can make one in under 20 lines of code with a shell scripting language like Bash. Similarly in most programming languages&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simplicity of the article, we won&#x27;t implement starting position, random initial character highlighting or anything too fancy. This implementation utilizes the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;vt100.net&#x2F;docs&#x2F;vt510-rm&#x2F;SGR.html&quot;&gt;Select Graphic Rendition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, specifically the 4-bit green color sequence for portability as well&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full-featured implementation, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;wick3dr0se&#x2F;matrix&quot;&gt;matrix digital rain I wrote in Bash&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (the inspiration for this post!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why-bash&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why-bash&quot;&gt;Why Bash?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash is an excellent choice for this, because Bash comes pre-installed nearly everywhere. Most of the time it&#x27;s the default shell interpreter. When writing pure Bash, it&#x27;s super portable and easy to write. Generally Bash performs pretty well if usage of shell invoking procedures (such as command substituion) and external calls are limited&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;concept&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#concept&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: concept&quot;&gt;Concept&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a general, base concept for a minimal matrix digital rain&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mind works well off concepts - In hopes it could help you, I&#x27;ll leave this here to give some context on the implementation&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;Trap exit - cleanup
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Initialize terminal
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Loop forever
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Calculate random column
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Calculate random speed
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Calculate random symbol length
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Loop - over terminal lines
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            Calculate random symbol
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            Print down calculated column
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            If iteration &amp;gt; symbol length, erase
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            Sleep (print speed)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    } Send to background
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    Sleep (print frequency)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#implementation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#x27;t have to use raw ANSI escape sequences, you can use an abstraction like &lt;code&gt;tput&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;wick3dr0se&#x2F;bashin&quot;&gt;TUI library I wrote&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for writing scripts exactly like this one, among others of course. But for performance and portability&#x27;s sake, it benefits to utilize ANSI escapes&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s start by initializing the terminal. How this works is up to you but I would utilize the terminal&#x27;s alternative buffer and disable the cursor. Using the alternative buffer has the advantage of disabling scrolling and allowing us to reset the terminal to its initial state&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sequences are &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;vt100.net&#x2F;docs&#x2F;vt100-ug&#x2F;&quot;&gt;VT100 ANSI escape sequences&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which are the standard, that terminal manipulation libraries abstract away&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;init_term&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# \e is an escape sequence
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# the following sequences switch to the alternative buffer and hide the cursor
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[?1049h\e[?25l&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# sets terminal x and y to COLUMNS&#x2F;LINES respectively
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;shopt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; -s checkwinsize; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where it gets a little interesting! We have to do some basic equations. Here we utilize Bash&#x27;s builtin &lt;code&gt;$RANDOM&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; variable to give us a random integer in the specified range. First we should calculate our symbols starting column, then our symbols printing delay and finally the amount of symbols to print down a column. We should loop over the terminal lines plus symbol length and calculate a random symbol&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it&#x27;s time to put all our random calculations to work! Simply print the random symbol to the calculated column down the iterated row (line) and follow up behind the symbol length with an erase sequence. Wrapping up our rain function, sleep with the calculated delay to give the rain varying speed. Almost there! This is the bulk of it, and the entire complexity of the implementation&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;rain&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# random column between 1-terminal columns
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolCol=RANDOM%COLUMNS+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# random sleep delay between 1-9
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolSpeed=RANDOM%&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;9&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# random length between 2-10
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolLen=RANDOM%&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;9&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# walk the terminal lines + symbol length
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(( i = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;; i &amp;lt;= LINES+symbolLen; i++ )); &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;do
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# random symbol
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;=&amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RANDOM&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;%$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# print green symbol down calculated column
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[%d;%dH\e[32m%s\e[m&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolCol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# erase after symbol length 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (( i &amp;gt; symbolLen )) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[%d;%dH\e[m &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;((i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;symbolLen))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolCol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# rain (printing) speed
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;sleep &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolSpeed&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;done
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After defining our functions, the script is super simple, only requiring a run forever loop and call to our rain function, sent to the background, with a short sleep delay to prevent our rain from absolute downpour and potential CPU havoc. Modifying the terminal state is completely optional but worth it&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defining some symbols as a string&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;=&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0123456789!@#$%^&amp;amp;*()-_=+[]{}|;:,.&amp;lt;&amp;gt;?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we should probably trap some terminal cleanup so that we can reset our terminal state. Although one could just opt to close the terminal, skipping deinitializing and trapping interrupts entirely. Arguably the next step should be done first but in TUI scripts, it&#x27;s common to define signal handlers before calling functions&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;trap &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;printf &amp;quot;\e[?1049l\e[?25h&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; SIGEXIT
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we initialize the terminal by calling our init_term function&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init_term
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish it off, we execute the run forever loop, call our rain function in the background and sleep between calls for density&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# loop forever
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((;;)) {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# call it and send it to the background
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    rain &amp;amp;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# rain density
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    sleep 0.1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s all!! Here is the entire implementation of our matrix digital rain in pure Bash using raw ANSI escape sequences, in under 20 lines of code!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;init_term&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[?1049h\e[?25l&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;shopt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; -s checkwinsize; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;rain&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolCol=RANDOM%COLUMNS+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolSpeed=RANDOM%&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;9&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ((symbolLen=RANDOM%&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;9&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(( i = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;; i &amp;lt;= LINES+symbolLen; i++ )); &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;do
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;=&amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RANDOM&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;%$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;{&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[%d;%dH\e[32m%s\e[m&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolCol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (( i &amp;gt; symbolLen )) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;printf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;\e[%d;%dH\e[m &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;((i&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;symbolLen))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolCol&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;sleep &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;$&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;symbolSpeed&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;done
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;trap &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;printf &amp;quot;\e[?1049l\e[?25h&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39; exit
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;SYMBOLS&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;=&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0123456789!@#$%^&amp;amp;*()-_=+[]{}|;:,.&amp;lt;&amp;gt;?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init_term
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((;;)) { rain &amp;amp; sleep 0.1; }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the post was thorough and able to teach you something! If not, well sorry, I tried! Anyway, you&#x27;re more than welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;wick3dr0se&#x2F;matrix&quot;&gt;support the project&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by dropping a star on GitHub!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Constraints</title>
        <published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/constraints/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/constraints/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/constraints/">&lt;p&gt;Author: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cyypherus&quot;&gt;cyypherus&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;constraints&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#constraints&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: constraints&quot;&gt;Constraints&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last year or so I&#x27;ve been on-and-off building a rust UI layout crate called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cyypherus&#x2F;backer&quot;&gt;backer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The project started with a very naive approach, as things usually do, where the layout tree is traversed, each node splitting the available area into segments or reducing the area available to children for padding.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfect! It couldn&#x27;t be more simple, why do frameworks complicate this so much! Let&#x27;s try our first layout.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to put my content in a row, with a fixed size-button in the first segment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;row&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(vec![
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;my_button&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;width&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;200.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;height&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;space&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;])
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;1.png&quot; alt=&quot;1&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fine, now what happens when the available area decreases?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;2.png&quot; alt=&quot;2&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the entire naive approach falls apart, everything is bad, &amp;amp; I am bad at software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;onward&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#onward&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: onward&quot;&gt;Onward!&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how should we handle the case where the parent is &quot;offered&quot; less space than it&#x27;s child needs? There needs to be some interaction between a container and it&#x27;s contents to ensure that we respect things like fixed size, &lt;em&gt;minimum size, or maximum size&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who builds UI is more than familiar with the beloved concept of &lt;strong&gt;constraints&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, &amp;amp; I needed to beef up my approach quite a bit. How should a constraint system be written &amp;amp; more importantly, how should it behave?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first, containers must check with their contents to see if there are any constraints they should follow to avoid ugly overlap like we saw earlier. The ideal result should look something like this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;3.png&quot; alt=&quot;3&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yellow segment has nothing in it, so it has no reason not to compress to make room for the element with the fixed size. It should be gladly willing to compress to a width of 0.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with this requirement, we want to respect minimum &#x2F; maximum constraints as well. Say we are laying out a row of elements that all have constraints on their widths. Our list of constraints looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;row&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(vec![
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;one&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;width_range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;50.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;75.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; &amp;gt;=50 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &amp;lt;=75
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;two&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;width_range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;110.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;150.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; &amp;gt;=110 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &amp;lt;=150
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;three&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;width_range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; &amp;lt;=10
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;four&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;width_range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;150&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; &amp;gt;=150
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;])
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have 400 units of space to divvy up, what&#x27;s next?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we fairly allocate space to each of the elements without breaking their constraints &amp;amp; ensuring we use &lt;strong&gt;exactly&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; 400 units of space?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;dread&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#dread&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: dread&quot;&gt;Dread&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a moment to consider it, this is actually quite tricky. The simplest approach I can imagine is to start with a guess, say, even allocation, and then nudge by tiny increments until the constraints are satisfied. Unfortunately, this can&#x27;t possibly scale well, and nudging floats is terribly ugly. Surely the internet has some quick answers!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, seems like all we need is a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Constraint_satisfaction_problem&quot;&gt;constraint solver&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;amp; it looks like the common solution in modern software is something called the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Cassowary_(software)&quot;&gt;Cassowary algorithm?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;amp; oh, god, cassowary is not simple at all. It&#x27;s heavy on some linear arithmetic &amp;amp; it has some strange features that I don&#x27;t necessarily even want - like the ability for constraints to be broken based on their level of priority?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&#x27;t seem to be a problem that is solved frequently, or at least not in a form I&#x27;m able to find.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it&#x27;s been effective in the past for me to let hard problems steep a while (in my head), &amp;amp; what else is there to do when you can&#x27;t solve something?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;aha-the-algorithm-appears&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#aha-the-algorithm-appears&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: aha-the-algorithm-appears&quot;&gt;Aha! The Algorithm Appears&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution arrives! (I think I was in the shower when it popped into my head, lol)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to our example, 400 units to divvy, &amp;amp; 4 elements with width constraints.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s start with even distribution.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we will check if any elements constraints are not satisfied with our initial state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;[100] (50..75) Bad!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[100] (110..150) Bad!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[100] (..10) Bad!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[100] (150..) Bad!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then shift the allocated amounts to the nearest amount that satisfies the constraints of each element.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial offering, 100, is the red line. The colored rectangles are the valid ranges that we need to satisfy, &amp;amp; the amount we&#x27;re shifting from the initial allocation is shown by the pale red &#x2F; pink lines.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;4.png&quot; alt=&quot;4&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;5.png&quot; alt=&quot;5&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we take space from an element we end up with extra space that needs to be filled - a surplus.
Likewise, when we give space to an element we are using space we may or may not have - a defecit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;[75] (50..75) 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[110] (110..150)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[10] (..10) 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[150] (150..)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Defecit: 10 + 50 = 60
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Surplus: 90 + 15 = 105
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Pool: 105 - 60 = 45
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;re now left with satisfied constraints, but some extra space in the pool that needs to be filled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to redistribute the surplus &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; breaking any constraints, &amp;amp; the only way to guarantee we aren&#x27;t breaking constraints is to sort the elements by the amount of space they&#x27;re allowed to consume.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both element one and element three are at their limit, but element two and four can both consume more space if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;6.png&quot; alt=&quot;6&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can now distribute excess starting with even distribution, or the smallest amount an element can consume - whichever is smaller.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, we&#x27;re lucky enough that the pool can be distributed evenly among the candidates but in other cases we have to make the distribution in increments (using the sort I mentioned) to ensure we don&#x27;t step over any constraint boundaries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;7.png&quot; alt=&quot;7&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;*Distribute 45 to the two available elements*
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[75] (50..75) Good!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[110 + 22.5 = 132.5] (110..150) Good!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[10] (..10) Good!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[150 + 22.5 = 172.5] (150..) Good!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, we&#x27;ve got a way to smoothly resolve constraints. The algorithm I&#x27;ve described is the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cyypherus&#x2F;backer&#x2F;blob&#x2F;0.11.1&#x2F;src&#x2F;layout.rs#L428&quot;&gt;algorithm&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; backer boasts today &amp;amp; the only reason ultra-smooth layout constraint resolution like this is possible with crates like the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;emilk&#x2F;egui&quot;&gt;egui&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;constraints&#x2F;nice.gif&quot; alt=&quot;nice&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading &amp;amp; happy coding :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>On boiling the ocean</title>
        <published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/on-boiling-the-ocean/"/>
        <id>https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/on-boiling-the-ocean/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensource-force.github.io/osf-blog/posts/on-boiling-the-ocean/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: from-the-desk-of-planetnineisaspaceship&quot;&gt;from the desk of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;planet-nine-app&#x2F;planet-nine&quot;&gt;planetnineisaspaceship&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-boiling-the-ocean&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-boiling-the-ocean&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: on-boiling-the-ocean&quot;&gt;On boiling the ocean&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you&#x27;ve got an idea.
You know it&#x27;s a great idea, and if enough people would just get on board it would be so awesome...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the business world, this is called boiling the ocean.
In business it&#x27;s a problem, when learning it can be great though, so let&#x27;s talk about it a bit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-history&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#some-history&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: some-history&quot;&gt;Some history&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t know if this is true, but it is hilarious so I&#x27;m going to quote it here:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boil the ocean idiom came about during World War I. When Will Rogers was asked how the US should go about the issue of German U-boats, he simply recommended this: Let the ocean be boiled. A reporter asked how this could be done. In response to this, Will Rogers replies, Man, Im just the idea. Source: theidioms.com&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty much everyone who works in tech has run into an idea like this.
When your job is to actually deliver working things to customers, boil the ocean ideas range from laughable to morale-killers.
Because of this they&#x27;re often met with doubt when brought to groups of industry folk, even if those folk are friendly and looking to help people learn (which if I&#x27;m being honest is not most groups of industry folk).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dunning-kruger&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#dunning-kruger&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: dunning-kruger&quot;&gt;Dunning-Kruger&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunning-Kruger is a cognitive bias where inexperienced people think things are simpler than they are, and experienced people also, but to a lesser degree, think things are simpler than they are.
When you combine these with a boil the ocean idea, you can have people who don&#x27;t know tech thinking, &quot;oh building this app would be so simple for an app developer,&quot; and experienced people thinking, &quot;this sounds easy, why don&#x27;t you just do it yourself.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, Dunning-Kruger is a pain in the keister, because it takes the form of some CEO telling you which database to use, but there&#x27;s this magical time before you realize how hard things are where you can do things that the curmudgeonly industry vets always talk themselves out of.
This is the land of Chris Sawyer, Tarn Adams, Notch, and ConcernedApe.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Tolkien spent two decades penning his Legendarium before he wrote the Lord of the Rings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-build-big-ideas&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#how-to-build-big-ideas&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: how-to-build-big-ideas&quot;&gt;How to build big ideas&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go into places where ideas get thrown around--startup forums, tech meetups--you&#x27;ll often hear ideas are easy&#x2F;cheap&#x2F;inconsequential, and that things like execution are what matter.
When it comes to making money, that&#x27;s kind of true I guess, but this doc&#x27;s not about making a startup.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth is, maybe ideas are easy, but only a handful of people who have them make the ridiculous leap to actually thinking they should make their idea happen.
I&#x27;m always reminded of what George Bernard Shaw said,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasonable man adapts himself to the world: the unreasonable one persists in trying to adapt the world to himself. Therefore all progress depends on the unreasonable man.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is why it&#x27;s important to understand what your motivations are in this big undertaking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-re-out-to-make-money&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#if-you-re-out-to-make-money&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: if-you-re-out-to-make-money&quot;&gt;If you&#x27;re out to make money&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said this isn&#x27;t a doc on how to make a startup, but I&#x27;ll say a few words about why boiling the ocean is the wrong strategy if money is your goal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money, in software, is best made by startups (if you&#x27;re not already an executive or something I guess), and for a startup to work you need two people: someone to build the thing, and someone to sell the thing.
Everyone who has done one or the other thinks their thing is the most important, and they&#x27;re both wrong, and it also doesn&#x27;t matter since worrying about which is which is a quick way to make it so you never sell the thing in the first place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not having skill in one thing or the other does not preclude you from taking on either role because they&#x27;re both &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to get good at (see Dunning-Kruger above).
And having your software product fail doesn&#x27;t necessarily mean you make no money (read &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;planet-nine-app&#x2F;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT having your software product be some gigantic thing when you don&#x27;t know how hard that is AND you actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the money you&#x27;re trying to make is a recipe for disaster.
So don&#x27;t do that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-not-money-than-what&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#if-not-money-than-what&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: if-not-money-than-what&quot;&gt;If not money than what?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well there are plenty of reasons to do things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future money (learning new skills, building a portfolio, etc)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the sake&#x2F;love of it&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To impress people&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better humanity and&#x2F;or the world&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it is awesome&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these, or anything else fits your case, then get on the boat friend, and let&#x27;s be unreasonable together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-started-before-you-start&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#get-started-before-you-start&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: get-started-before-you-start&quot;&gt;Get started before you start&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the following sections I&#x27;m going to assume you&#x27;ve chosen to build whatever it is you want.
If instead you want to sell it, I&#x27;m going to have to ask you to look elsewhere for guidance, lest I Dunning-Kruge myself on sales.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first big projects I started was building a random music generator.
Nowadays I&#x27;m sure there&#x27;s some AI-assisted music generators out there, but this was like 2001, and playing tones of any kind from a computer was pretty arcane.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big software projects are, usually, &lt;em&gt;systems&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
That is they are multiple software programs running in a cohesive unit to do whatever it is you&#x27;re trying to do.
In a big company you would have a systems architect or two who put together system architecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me show you some system architecture:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource-force.github.io&#x2F;osf-blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;on-boiling-the-ocean&#x2F;system_architecture.png&quot; alt=&quot;A very basic system architecture diagram&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m sure you can see why they make the big bucks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Break your project down into parts like this.
The specifics of the parts aren&#x27;t really important.
What&#x27;s important is your ability to articulate what the parts do and how they fit into your project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my random music generator I had a UI where you could pick things like keys and tempos, and I had the tone generator that built the tones via math based on the UI, and I had the song generator which put the tones in order based on musical rules.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general the way to build your project is to just keep breaking down these boxes into smaller boxes until you hit a box that you feel you can do.
Then you do that box.
Just like eating an elephat--one bite at a time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-need-help&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#i-need-help&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: i-need-help&quot;&gt;I need help&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, here&#x27;s the thing with big ideas, and really sharing things at all, when you share, you&#x27;re sharing something you&#x27;ve thought about for months, or years, but the person you&#x27;re talking to has just heard about what you&#x27;re trying to tell them.
So big ideas tend to be just plain overwhelming to people when they first hear them.
Really all ideas are kind of overwhelming when people first hear them--especially if they don&#x27;t trust you to have good ideas yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means if you&#x27;re trying to recruit people, don&#x27;t hit them with the whole idea of the back, instead focus on the first box you&#x27;re trying to build.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people make the mistake of trying to find people to commit to their project, but that&#x27;s not really how things work in the (software) world.
Life happens, and priorities shift around.
If I had a nickel for each time someone working with me on a project disappeared because they started seeing someone new, I&#x27;d have enough nickels to rehire some of them to work on the projects for real.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can, and should, plan on committing all of the code and design yourself.
If you get help, great, if not the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; help comes with the conversations you have with people who you bring along the way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-end-in-sight&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#no-end-in-sight&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: no-end-in-sight&quot;&gt;No end in sight&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Survivorship bias is a hell of a drug.
It gives the illusion that success is a linear process, and one that simply starts at day one and grows.
It is not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in high school, my friends and I used to call it the 99% pile.
99% of all creative endeavors: music, art, code, etc, end up thrown away either not good enough or unfinished.
Now that I&#x27;m older it&#x27;s probably closer to 99.99%.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn&#x27;t mean we don&#x27;t try.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your dream takes five years to build, take five years to build it.
If it&#x27;s no longer your dream after three years, find another dream.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been working on mine for six and a half.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-on-the-boat&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#get-on-the-boat&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: get-on-the-boat&quot;&gt;Get on the boat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I remember hearing that we didn&#x27;t know how people got to Hawaii.
I was like, &quot;that&#x27;s dumb. Of course we know. They got there by boat.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s what we do as humans.
You put some barrier in front of us, and we&#x27;ll figure out how to go over, under, or around it to find what&#x27;s out there.
We&#x27;re explorers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You had an idea, built a boat, and now the island&#x27;s telling you not to go.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows where the boat&#x27;s gonna take you?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it worth it to you to find out?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose solo game developers here because though some may have knwon programming, there&#x27;s sooooo much more that goes into making games that I don&#x27;t think it&#x27;s a huge stretch to say they had a touch of the Dunning-Kruger at the onset of their endeavors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ol&#x27; George penned Man and Superman in 1903, the same year Madame Curie was awarded the Nobel Prize for the first time. A writer friend of mine once admonished me for editing quotes to modern sensibilities of gender and race, but this quote, like the tech industry, and society in general is stupidly patriarchal, and I can&#x27;t let it slide without comment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
